He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc.
Chapter 48 verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons, and saints.
an hour time.
yearned to break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show, focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and explain
experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Christ is risen, He truly is risen.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers,
hemadryad hackers.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D. Young,
the overeducated Mars troll is with me
straight from the swamp in Lafayette, Louisiana.
My father, and just Stephen Damien,
can amaze Pennsylvania,
perched precariously atop the arcane tower
of podcasting, hovering dozens, dozens of stories
above a disused gateway to the underworld.
and we...
our lives. If you're listening to us live, you can call us 8552372346. You can talk to us.
We're going to get your calls beginning in the second half. And to Mike, Tinpan, Deadpan,
again, we'll be taking your calls. I should say, by the way, just as a side comment that we have sold out
all of the rooms for the Laura Spirits conference. But there's still plenty of commuter tickets available.
So you can head to your store.intensfit.com slash events to get yours. That's the first weekend of our
the
car.
And then you can just go
in the car and then come
wandering into the village
every day.
You may not sleep.
Well, if you're going to
sleep in your car, you may
not be in the parking lot of
the village.
They will find you.
They will spend you.
You know, you know the cop
come on.
The local
constabulary will be
contacted.
Just going full
care on the parking lot
at the village.
That's right.
You have better
things to do.
That's right.
to continue.
are three part series on the history of Israel. This is part two. We're going to pick up
after the Exodus. Before we start though, Father, there's something that's been bothering
me, just a big lacuna in my head. I know that Professor Carter-
I don't believe that this has really been bothering you that much.
It has. This is a question that came up in my head today. It did. But so Professor Bart
Irman has been anointed as a friend of the show, but I have to ask whether there are others.
I mean, are there qualifications for this?
There are no other friends of the show.
He's the one and only friend of the show.
Solamente, Mark Herrmann.
Wow.
Because being a friend of the show gives you the right to call in at any time for any amount
of time that'd be put through.
I mean, we've gotten close.
We've been contacted by a relative of his.
Yeah.
Really close relative.
He is the only friend of the show.
Uh.
Yeah, and you know, so we haven't taken shots at him though. We've taken shots at some other people like that's true
I mean you've occasionally disagreed with him. Yes, but right yeah, so he's a further show so before we start I need to
Get something off my chest. Oh, oh, okay, and that's related to
A comment that we've got we got on some of the stuff with the last episode. Oh
Oh, yes.
No, it's not the one you think. Oh man.
And I know I kind of love.
I love dispensationless tears though. I do.
The but this is a comment that we've gotten on. I've gotten at least on other things in the past.
Talking about the Torah and stuff.
And that is this comment where someone says something on the order of.
God gave the Torah.
to show that we couldn't keep it.
Oh, yes, this is totally a thing.
And that we needed a savior.
Get a look.
I know somebody taught you this.
Right?
This is just what you're taught.
You haven't really thought about it.
Same thing for them.
The person who taught it to you probably was taught to them
and they never thought about it.
And on and on and on.
Right?
Back to Martin Luther who thought about it.
they should have thought better.
Let's think about this for a second.
What are you saying when you say that?
Okay.
You're saying God came up with a list of commandments
that no human could keep.
Okay. Well, he certainly could do that, right?
That wouldn't be hard.
He's God.
Right. You could come up with a list of commandments
that no human could keep if you wanted to.
Right.
But you're saying he did this, that's what the Torah is.
And he did that to show us the lead to us.
So first of all, what you're saying is that in Deuteronomy 30 verse 11, where God says,
what I am commanding you today is not too difficult for you.
and continues to elaborate that they have a choice to keep the commandments are not.
Not to put too fine a point on it, but you're calling God a liar.
You're saying God gave them this command. It's knowing that not that they wouldn't,
not knowing that they wouldn't keep it, but knowing that they couldn't keep it.
But then told them they could.
Then told them they could. And then when they didn't, he punished them for it.
And let's be clear on what that punish
was in the Old Testament. We are talking about thousands of human beings like you
and me, okay, who were gutted, massacred, raped, taken into slavery, women and
children, okay? Suffer this horrible fate for not keeping commandments that God
gave them newing they couldn't do it.
And why did God do this and then lie about it and then massacre all these people?
What was all this mayhem for?
All this mayhem was so that you, bourgeois 21st century American, would know that it's
not enough for you to just try to be a good person.
You need to believe the four spiritual laws.
I thought you were going to say it's all for his
glory. Yeah. Not even that. The Calvinist are ahead of y'all this one. Yeah. It's so that you
would know, oh, hey, I shouldn't bother trying to keep that Torah thing or keep the manments. Look
at what happened to them. I should just believe the four spiritual laws. Thank you, thousands of dead
children. I'm also trying to map that on to like parenting, right? Like what if I made rules for my
I knew that they could not keep and then I
lie to them and told them they could lie them and told they could and then punish them severely when they did not.
Yes. Yes. So that the next generation, so that a future generation of Damicks could look back at this object less than you had acted.
And say, Hey, you know what? We should just depend on the love and mercy of our parents and not try to be good.
Okay. Yeah.
This is blasphemy, guys.
Bless for me, bless for you.
Yes, sir.
What, what, when you say that, I know you haven't thought it through.
I know you're not intentionally blasphemy, right?
But it is blasphemy.
What, what that says about God is blasphemy.
So stop saying that.
Okay.
It contradicts scripture.
It says that God is a liar, right?
And the level of like modernist arrogance required to think that all of these
broadsage people's lives and souls were just expensive.
So that you could learn a moral from the story, right? It's kind of obscene.
So don't post that comment anymore.
And if that is like a load bearing piece of your paradigm, which I know for some of you, it is that no one can keep the door, right?
Like you're going to have to rearrange your paradigm.
Because we're not done with that idea tonight.
Yes, right. We're not done with that idea because the flip side of that is the people in
the Bible who did keep the whole Torah, the Bible says they did. Right? So that whole
paradigm you're working from that would cause you to make that comment, needs to just go
out the window. Contrary scripture, it's blasphemous. We don't need it. Right? We don't
We don't want it.
We shouldn't have it. So there we go now that I've called half of our audience. Last Vimers
on with the show. You're on notice. Okay. So how about that Joshua guy?
They did not get a tip of the hat. They got a wag of the finger. I say you like that segue.
So about that Joshua guy. Yeah. Hey, how about a never something completely different?
although not completely different.
Yeah, so.
Last time on Lord of Spirits, now if we were professional, we'd have some clips to play,
right?
Like, edit together to a montage, to recap and get us cut up to where we are.
But basically, we're in Israel's history at the point of Israel entering into the land
of Canaan, which means Joshua, right?
if you're reading.
in the Greek Jesus, just, and you know,
if you're one of those types, you know.
I don't know which is more annoying to me,
the people who'd sit on calling Jesus Yeshua
or the people who had sit on calling Joshua
in the Old Testament Jesus.
Oh, my favorite, they're both up there.
My favorite there are the people that like insist on something
like Yahoshua or something like that.
Oh, that's even worse.
Yeah.
Right, I know.
Yeah, that's a little bit there, buddy.
That's heading into like Black Hebrew Israelite.
how to pronounce Yahweh territory.
Right.
That's yeah.
So, but yeah, so we were talking about Joshua,
the son of Nun, right?
Not Jesus, the son of Navi.
Yeah.
Get out of here with that.
You're not Greek.
The cultural appropriation.
And if you are Greek, you should be saying Jesus.
Anyhow.
Jesus
So, and obviously we're not, we've got a through line, if you listen to the last episode.
And if not, press pause on this live episode and go back and listen to the last two weeks ago's episode.
No. So the thing we need to take into account when we're talking about the conquest, Joshua's conquest,
quest for a number of reasons that we're going to get into is.
Joshua's conquest is not about the Israelites depopulating completely a piece of land.
Right. Not everybody is either killed or removed in fact. Right.
This is how we'll get framed to you by people who haven't actually read the Bible mostly,
but that is not what happens here in the Bronze Age.
maybe
happening now, but it's not happening. It didn't happen then. Right. Okay. It didn't happen
then. So that's not what the story is about. Okay. The atheists who throw this out as an
argument are fascinating to me. Right? Because only like really conservative scholars, which
is a small minority of biblical scholars.
Right. Really conservative, mostly Protestant conservative biblical scholars
Hold that everything in the book of Joshua is literally true. I'm not saying I don't I'm just saying that's a minority among scholars, right?
Most scholars
biblical scholars are
More liberal than that. We'll say yeah, okay most will say it's some kind of yes metaphor or right
Yeah, right or at the very least that there's like hyperbole and stuff, right?
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, you know when it says these people were completely destroyed that's just sort of like saying you know our football team completely destroyed the other right it's not little right
So right so so yet when an atheist wants to make this argument they argue as if like everything in the book of Joshua is historical fact
Why they believe that is an atheist I don't know
Right like
Okay, but this is a common problem with atheist arguments.
It's like they read the Bible like they're a fundamentalist.
And then like, yeah, that's how people read the Bible.
But anyways, that's how it's presented to you is just this.
Genesis, God commands them to go and genocide everyone living in this area
because he's giving them the land.
Okay.
Now we already saw last time a little bit when we were talking about the other
Abraham Abrahamite groups. The itemites the Moabites.
the Amonites at all. The Amonites being the descendants of Ammon, not like the
little fossil critters, that there were a list of people who they had displaced,
right specific people groups, right, had been driven out before them. Not
everyone who lived there. And this is the case.
for Israel as well in terms of the land of Canaan.
It's not every person who lives in Canaan.
Every man who a child gainer is gonna get massacred.
That's not what's like.
It was not just like sort of a genocide,
you know, kill and drive out every person to take this land.
But there are particular identified groups
that this is true not only like in the book of Joshua,
but this is true from the time the promises
are given to Abraham, right?
So like a Genesis 15,
Yeah, after God makes the covenant with Abraham with the split animals, right?
Yeah, talked about it on the show before.
Pretty memorable moment.
I can't give you the product movie.
Yeah, movie the life of Abraham, the camera just pants away.
Yeah, so Genesis 15 verses 18 through 21 says on that day the Lord made a covenant with
Abram saying, to your offspring, I give this land from the river of Egypt to the Great
River, the river you freighties, the land of the Kenites, the Kennesites, the Cat
the Hittites, the Parasites, the Refaim, the Emirates, the Canaanites, the Gurgishites, and the Jebysites.
Right. So already in there, it's not just, hey, this geographic piece of land, but it's, there are these groups.
Right. Giant Clans. Right. Who are living in a, who you are going to drive out and displace and take the,
but
their land, right?
As a judgment.
That's there.
And remember, as we mentioned already, Deuteronomy chapter 4, when Israel is growing close to
these nations in the transjordan who are also Abrahamite nations, they're told you're
not to take any land from Edom because God gave Edom that piece of land, which is a
piece of this land that was given to Abraham.
that has been given to his descendant, Edom, but also listed there are the names of the
giant clans that the Edomites drove out.
So you can't separate these two things in Scripture.
These are not two separate things, taking possession of this land, driving out the giant
clans.
They're one reality.
You can't separate.
the two. Not two separate things. Now, obviously, we have a whole episode on giants. Indeed.
We're not going to rehearse that whole episode now. Press pause on this live broadcast. Go
go back and listen to that episode as well. Welcome back from your
rarer to this. Right. So but
A couple of things that are important reminders for this.
Number one, what made you a member of a clan,
what made you a particularite of whatever kind, right,
was part ritual participation in the rituals of that people.
So remember, as we talked about last time,
what made you an Israelite was if you were male being circumcised,
If you're a female being the wife or dog
of a circumcised male. Yeah, you're not just born into it. There has to be a ritual process.
And then eating the Passover. Right. Every year. That's what makes you an Israelite.
Well, likewise, there were rituals among all these other people groups that the Egyptians
had a ritual life that may constitute them as Egyptians. Right.
etc. That's how this was viewed.
So the giant
Clans who are being singled out have a particular type of ritual life, okay, which includes
human sacrifice, cannibalism, right? Sort of gross sexual immorality in a pagan worship context,
Right? All of these, all of these things together. These aren't just, oh, some of them do these bad.
things, right? Participating in these things as a group is what makes them a
Gurgishite or a Reffing, right? That's what makes them that.
That means two things. Number one, no one who's participated in those things is innocent,
But number two, anyone who stops,
participating in those ritual acts and
goes and joins another people is no longer one of those people. So a
Gurgishite who stops participating in the human sacrifice and the sexual
morality, et cetera, going on among the Gurgishites and goes and moves
to Egypt and begins to participate in the ritual life of Egypt is now an Egyptian.
Egyptian. Yeah, the remember we don't.
No DNA exists. There's not a concept of heredity yet. There's not a concept of ethnicity yet.
Right. You are a member of a group, but you're a member of that group because you're participating
with that group. And this is this reality, right, that someone can leave the Gurgishite. It's
it's a dollar to be a girl, that someone can leave a giant clan and become something else.
Okay. Is right there in the text of the Torah in Joshua.
You have, I mean, there's a big example.
Yeah.
Caleb, right?
Yes.
Not probably, you know, almost certainly not a descendant of Abraham in the, in the
biology.
No, he is not because he's identified as a kinesite, which is one of these
other groups.
One of these giant clans.
Oh, man.
So he's an ex giant, not just a pagan group.
Right.
What is first?
introduced, he's a Kenezite, one of those groups who was in that list from Genesis 15, we just read.
He's one of those people. But by the end of his story in the book of Joshua, he's an elder of the
tribe of Judah. Okay? See, he's no longer a Kenezite. Right? So what is being commanded here, what God is
commanding is...
There must be no more kinetics, no more girgishites, no more refaim, right? No more amurites.
That doesn't mean every single man, woman and child has to die. That means they have to no longer
practice those rituals. I mean, like, like Rahab and Jericho, right? She's no longer, I don't know,
what you would call those people Jerichoites. Well, Rahab is named after one of the chaos dragons
right right yeah that serves yum they're like low tan aka
rava Leviathan and rahaav that's what Ray Habs name comes from yeah right so
she becomes part of Israel and indeed an ancestor of our Lord yes so again this
is not about the humans it's not about genetics it's not about any of that
those concepts didn't exist this is about and if you read closely God keeps
talking about
about, you was put into the abominations of these groups. Right? So if all of the
Gurgishites are either dead or have stopped being Gurgishites and there are no more Gurgishites,
the Gurgishites have been wiped out from the perspective of Scripture. That doesn't
mean a bunch of them are going to get killed because a bunch of them, you know, you can
Imagine people who frequently practice human sacrifice of their n-
and enemies probably aren't going to just be like,
yeah, you know, you're right.
We should knock this stuff off.
Let's all go become Israelites.
Yeah.
Right?
Like some of them ain't going to go quietly, right?
So, right?
But as I pointed out to people several times,
if you knew for a fact, people get very concerned,
oh, this is horrible.
How can you kill those people?
Right, if you knew for a fact that you're neighbor.
was sacrificing people, sacrificing humans to a demon and participating in
cannibalism, your next door neighbor. Would you just like pray for him? It's just
their culture man. Or would you like to sit there and pray for him? Oh, show him
the error of his ways Lord. Or would you call the police? Yeah, right. Exactly. I'm
I'm thinking...
you would call a bunch of men with guns and women. And those men and women with guns would
go into your neighbor's house and they would stop your neighbor from killing anymore people,
from sacrificing anymore people. And if the only way to do that, or if he resisted them
and attacked them, they would shoot him. And I submit to you that if that's what happened,
And that had to happen to stop him from killing people and eating them.
You would
feel that bad about it. If you are a very kind soul, you would pray for his soul after
his death, and that would be a good thing to do. But you would agree that the murder and
stuff needed to be stopped. That's what we're talking about. Okay. We're not talking
about just random men, women and children, and minding their own business, and all of
a sudden these Israelites come flying out of the woodwork and slaughter them all. Okay,
That's not what we're talking about.
about putting an end to nightmarish horrors.
Yeah.
And also if you're concerned about women and children
at that part of the world and the Bronze Age,
how about now?
Okay, but we'll continue.
I know you don't wanna comment on that,
but seems the Bronze Age inhabitants of the land
age inhabitants of the land seem to get a lot more sympathy from a lot of
contemporary people. I think it's probably a lot of
coincidence. Yeah, because I think people, I think a lot of it is that our culture, our
world really has been so Christianized that it's hard to imagine that there are whole
cultures that are built on doing that kind of horrible stuff. But yeah, all the evidence
that exists points to that being real.
Yeah. And even even like that existed.
not that long ago. Yeah, right. And even like, like the Romans, for instance, who are a brutal
predatory apex predator of the Mediterranean, right? They look at groups that they're aware of
child sacrifice. Child sacrifice in groups and say, those are freaks. Yeah. You know, if the
Romans think you're a freak, you're pretty bad. And that's the, these are the groups that are
being driven out of Canaan, you know, and being being, you know, that this way of life.
has to end. Yes. So, uh, right. And so this is the story that's being told. Now, if you want to say to
me, Hey, all that giant stuff is nonsense. Uh, that story of Joshua, is it true? I'm going to say,
Well, okay, fine. You can believe that. But then it's kind of hard to criticize the Bible about a
story that you don't think is true. Zeebswer.
because that's the core of what's going on, right?
But also, right, why is this important?
Because you and I have never met a Gurgishite
or an amulacite or any of,
and one of the Anachim, right?
We haven't met any of these people groups, right?
They're long gone.
So why is it so important that this is preserved
the text over and over and over
over again. And as you read through the Torah and Joshua, it is over and over and over and over again
that you get this list of people groups of the giant clans. Yeah. Right. Why is it so important
that that's there and that the names of these groups long extinct are preserved there?
And it's making a point. Right. And in the end of the Torah and the blessings and curses there put
to find her point on this point, but from the very beginning
The land which as we said last time is a sign is real coming in taking possession of the land was assigned to them of the truth of the larger promise
Right of becoming like the stars of heaven
Right of eternal life of theosis that's the pros taking the land is this sign right but the land always had this conditionality attached to it.
it. Yeah, it's not an automatic or unconditional.
right. That land had been given by God to those groups. Yeah. Yeah. How the God wasn't involved.
Right. Right. Everything that a creature has, they have because God gave it to them. That's
right. Right. But now because of their wickedness and their abominations, they're being driven out.
Right. And that implies what you know, Leviticus 26 and Deuteronomy 28 through 30 are going to
to state plainly that
If and when Israel becomes like them, they too will suffer the same fate.
Same with Adam, same with Moab, same with Ammon, same with Egypt for that matter,
same with every nation in the history of the world.
There is a conditionality to the land.
land. And so the fact that
this belonged to another group that other group lost it, right?
Is a reflection of that conditionality.
That dynamic may remind you of some things in the New Testament,
like Christ's parable of the vineyard.
Yeah,
where at the end of the vineyard is taken away from the wicked man and given to
others who will bring forth fruit from it.
Yeah.
Right. So this is this is a paradigm that's in Scripture. Right. That there's a conditionality.
To the promises of God. Yeah, these are not inalienable rights. Yes. Or rights at all. Yeah.
that are gifts. Right. So and and it's also important because this and
involves some of the most boring parts of the Old Testament. And
therefore the least read this involves a big chunk of the book of
numbers. The latter part of Joshua after all the exciting
battles are over. This isn't just, okay, Israelite's here's
land, right? No, it's this bit is for y'all this bit is for
y'all, you know, it's right, it's uh...
And this is from God.
This is straight from God.
That says this tribe gets this part, this tribe gets this part.
And even beyond tribes, it gets way more granular than that.
Yeah.
It's this plan within the tribe and this family within the clan.
And it's very notable, of course, that the Levites do not get land, because as it says,
that their inheritance is God himself.
Right.
Yeah.
But so it's very particular and then the whole
system of the Torah is set up around the idea that that land belongs to that family. Remember,
every 50th year, that land, all that land is supposed to revert back to the original family
ownership.
Yeah, big.
That's the Jubilee year, right?
That's the big economic reset.
50th year. It's supposed to all go back every
seven after seven sevens right so seven sets of seven years seven Sabbath years
then you have the Jubilee year we're going to come back to this later Israel never celebrated
the Sabbath year let alone the Jubilee right so again this order in the Torah that was set out
for what Israel was supposed to be never actually came to fruition never actually existed
but that's what's in the Torah. That's what God commanded.
right that these very particular and it's not just when I say it never existed. I don't mean
well yeah when it started out God gave them the land and they all moved into it but then very
quickly it went awry no no no no no no it didn't even start right okay so very early on as soon
as they defeat Og.
the last of the Refi'im and
Cihon the king of the Emirates
It's not it's not Chris was still August dead
But as soon as they defeat them Ruben Gad the tribe say hey, you know what we kind of like this land in the trans Jordan good luck y'all
So this is the land that's east of the Jordan River everybody. Yes, like not israel proper
Yes.
Yes, that that August Ceyron had taken from the Moabites.
Yeah, I mean, this is, this is the area that now is
the country of Jordan.
Yeah.
And so, you remember what Trans and SIS were just talking
about the Jordan River?
A happy, simpler time.
The Garland days.
Um, so that's, um, but.
and then Ruben and get there sort of a settlement that gets negotiated where they're kind of
allowed to do that, but only after they come and help with help the other tribes take,
take their portions. But even then there's some dicey stuff like they build an altar
over there. And these really as good as, hey, what's with the altar over there? They're
No, it's a replica.
So that when our kids ask us what.
the altar looks like we could point at it and say it looks like that. That's literally
their excuse. Yeah. So there's a lot of dodgy stuff going on there, but then you get
the tribe of Dan, which goes beyond dodgy. Okay. So we talked a little bit about the origins
of Dan last time that these
are actually primarily one of the C-peoples, if we want to talk about for the
perspective of modern ethnicity. But the Danites, now what happens is God says
to each of the tribes that he lays out these land grants. That's before they
actually take the land. And the tribes are supposed to go and take the land that
God is directing them too.
Yeah, it's not like God said, look at this lovely pad site.
I have approved for you to just build on.
Yeah.
You know, there's there's people there and the tribe has to go and do battle.
And God says, I'm going to lead you into battle when there's battle, right?
But you go and take possession of it and they're supposed to be faithful to that.
And that's how they're actually going to receive their inheritance, receive their portion.
Okay.
Yeah.
So God, as with the other tribes, directs Dan toward a particular piece of land.
You
And then things happen.
Yeah.
They don't like that land.
So what you get in Joshua 19,
starting with the verse 40,
this has a lot of good,
fun,
Middle Eastern names.
The seventh lot came out for the tribe of the people of Dinn,
according to their clans.
And the territory of its inheritance included Zura,
Estaule,
Irsemus Salabin Aizalin
Islam, Islam, Timnah, Ekron, don't get triggered because I said,
Elon, by the way, El-Tak, Gibbathan, Baalath, Jehud, Ben-A-Berek, Kathriman, and Mejarkan
and Rakan, with the territory over against Japa. When the territory of the people of Dan
was lost to them, the people of Dan went up and fought against Lesham. And after capturing
it and striking it with the sword they took possession of it.
and settle it in it, calling Lesham Dan after the name of Dan their ancestor. This is the
inheritance of the tribe of the people of Dan according to their clans. These cities with their
villages. So not only did they not take the places with all those fun names, they went over to this
other city instead. And took the city. And we're going to get more detail on that in a second. But
obviously I don't have the ability to draw you a bad map over the radio here. But where's Japa?
Yeah, that's on the coast.
Well, that's where my wife's ancestors are from.
I don't know.
Yafa.
And where's the city of Dan?
I'm not sure about that.
The extreme north.
They were near the coast.
Okay.
There you go.
So it's not like they went to a different spot with all the bail people up there up north.
Yes.
It was arguably.
But they were arguably given a better spot.
Yeah.
Right.
But didn't go take it.
Seacost is good.
Right.
Now that they've been taking the link.
and that God was going to give them they did something else.
And so now in Judges 18,
there is a much more detailed version of the same story.
Okay, so strap in everybody.
This is more than like five verses.
In fact, this is Judges 18.
In those days, there was no king in Israel.
That's always a clue right there
when it starts that way.
And in those days, the tribe of the people of Dan
was seeking for itself an inheritance to dwell in.
Until then, no-
inheritance among the tribes of Israel had fallen to them. So the people of Dan sent five
able men from the whole number of their tribe, from Zora and from Estau to spy out the land
and to explore it, and they said to them, go and explore the land. And they came to the
hill country of Ephraim, to the house of Micah, and lodged there. When they were by the house of Micah,
they recognized the voice of the young Levite, and they turned aside and said to him,
who brought you here? What are you doing in this place? What is your business here? And he said to
of them. This is how Mike.
dealt with me. He has hired me and I have become his priest." And they said to him,
and choir of God, please, that we may know whether the journey in which we are sitting out will succeed.
And the priest said to them, go and peace, the journey in which you go is under the eye of the Lord.
They had paused a second. Yeah. So we're already at point. We're not that far into Israel's history.
We've got wandering priests for hire. Right, exactly. This is just some guy from the tribe of
I'm e-freium, just hired this guy.
is Levi to be his priest.
You're Levi come do the magic stuff for us.
Yes.
Right.
And you notice they said in choir of God, it doesn't say he went and
inquired.
Yeah, he just said, it's good.
You're good.
He just gave him the whammy.
Right.
All right.
Then the five men departed and came to Laish and saw the people who
were there, how they lived in security after the manner of the
sedonians quiet and unsuspecting, lacking nothing that is in
the earth and possessing wealth and how they were far from the
Donions and had no dealings with anyone. And when they came to their brothers at Zora and
Eshtaw, their brothers said to them, what do you report? They said, arise and let us
go up against them. But we have seen the land and behold it is very good. And will you
do nothing to not be slow to go to enter and possess the land as soon as you go, you
will come to an unsuspecting people. The land is spacious. For God has given it into
your hands, a place where there is no lack of anything that is in the earth.
So they go out, they find the city that its admirons.
right the farmland around it.
And they say, these are peaceful people.
And they're some kind of Phoenicians,
that's the connection to the Scydonians.
But they're far away from Sidonians
so the Scydonians won't be able to get there
and help them.
It's like Vikings visiting Lindisfar.
Yes.
Why?
And they're literally just like,
oh, I smell a prey animal, right?
Right.
Exactly.
Yes.
Come, let us pick on someone not our own size.
Okay.
Okay, yes, so 600 men of the tribe of Dan armed with weapons of war set out from Zora
and Estal and went up and encamped at Kiryath Jerem in Judah.
On this account, that place is called Mahana Dan to this day.
Behold, it is west of Kiryath Jerem.
And they passed on from there to the hill country of Ephraim and came to the house of Micah.
Then the five men who had gone to scout out the country of Laïsh said to their brothers,
Do you know that in these houses there are an effod household gods a carved image?
and a metal image. Now, therefore, consider what you will do. And they turn the side there and
came to the house, the young Levite at the home of Micah, and asked him about his welfare. So,
so how they how they how they pay you there, buddy. Yeah. Pause again. Just to make clear, right?
He he doesn't have an ultra-out there. He's offering sacrifices to Yahweh to just doing it in the
wrong place. New. Okay. He has his own ephod like the high priest. Yeah. Right.
Household God's plural.
An idol, a carbidol, and an idol made of metal.
Yeah. Right? It's the day I say,
hey, this is all valuable stuff, by the way.
This guy let us stay with him.
Well, we're on our way to the city.
Let's rob this guy.
Oh, there.
Yes. Yes.
All right.
Now, the 600 men of the Danites armed with weapons of war
stood by the entrance of the gate
and the five men who had gone to scout out the land
went up and entered and took the carved image,
the e-fod, the household gods, and the metal image
while the priest stood by the entrance of the gate
with 600 men armed with weapons of war.
And when these went into Micah's house
and took the carved image, the e-fod,
the household gods and the metal image,
the priest said to them, what are you doing?
And they said to him, keep quiet,
your hand on your mouth and come with us.
And be to us the father in a priest is it better for you to be priest to the house of one man or to be
priest to a tribe and clan in Israel. The priest, tart was glad. He took the ephod in the household
gods and the carved image and went along with the people. So they turned into parted putting the
little ones and the livestock and the goods in front of them. This was the first priest to move from
a tiny church to a bigger church. It's tart was glad because he saw more money. Indeed.
when they got a distance from the home
of Micah, the men who are in the houses near Micah's house were called out.
And they overtook the people of Dan.
And they shout at the people of Dan who turned around and said to Micah,
what is the matter with you that you come with such a company?
And he said, you take my gods that I made and the priest and go away.
And what have I left?
How then do you ask me what is the matter with you?
And the people of Dan said to him, do not let your voice be heard among us.
Let angry fellows fall upon you and you lose your life with the lives of your household.
Then the people of Dan went their way.
I don't like a saw that
they were too strong for him, he turned back and went to his home.
So they threatened to kill him.
Right.
We don't want to hear, you know, shut up straight up rob this guy or some shelter.
Angry fellows will fall upon you.
But the people of Dan took what Micah had made and the priest who belonged to him and they
came to Laish to a people quiet and unsuspecting and struck them with the edge of the sword and
burn the city with fire.
And there was no deliver because it was far from Siden and they had no dealings with anyone.
It was in the valley that belonged to Bethrohub. Then they rebuilt the city and lived in it,
and they named the city Dan, after the name of Dan their ancestor was born to Israel. But the name
of the city was Laesh at the first, and the people of Dan set up the carved image for themselves,
and Jonathan the son of Gershom, son of Moses and his sons were priests to the tribe of the
the denights until the day of the captivity of the land. So they set up Micah's
this carbon emissions that he made.
as long as the House of God was at Shiloh.
So this Levite was not from just any clan among the Levites, he was a descendant of Moses.
Yeah, right.
Just a few generations.
Yes.
Yeah.
So things went south very fast.
Right?
In terms of religion.
This is bad.
and add big
was thinking about what we were just told there in judges. I know people have a lot of people
haven't read this chapter of judges because you get to the end of the Samsung story and you stop
because it gets weird and violent and not as interesting and fun. Um, all those, the Samsung
stories so kind of weird and violent as well. Well, yeah, but, you know, yeah, people try to make
make him a hero. But this is the priesthood.
of Dan has its own priesthood from this point. So from just after the time of Joshua,
right, until the northern kingdom of Israel's tribe of Dan ceased to exist under the Assyrians,
that whole time they have their own priesthood based on idolatrous shrines in the city of Dan.
They are not participating in the religion of well.
anything like the religion described in the Torah and not even the
malformed version of it that was going on in Judah, right?
Just Dan, I Dollar Trust start to finish. Samson being from the tribe of Dan, remember.
Yeah. So Dan is sort of the most egregious example of, right? Like
Those land grants were pretty much
ignored. Yeah. A lot of the tribes failed to take what they were supposed to and that
some of them like Dan just went predator and went and stole some other land in cities
that they weren't supposed to. Nonetheless, sorry, dispensationalist friends. Yes. I know
I know you took the last episode a little hard.
this is not going to be good for you. Right. So if I was hammering at a weight bearing pillar before,
yeah, brace yourself. All right. So we're going to we're going to read some Bible to you at the end of the book of Joshua.
Yep. Yeah. What is the result, according to the book of Joshua, of what Joshua accomplished during Joshua's lifetime in the late bronzing?
Okay, Joshua 21 starting with the verse 43. Thus
The Lord gave to Israel all the land that He swore to give to their fathers, and they
took possession of it and they settled there.
Pause a second.
I would like you to read that verse one more time.
Thus the Lord gave to Israel all the land that He swore to give to their fathers and they
took possession of it and they settled there.
So all the land that was promised as of Joshua chapter 20, verse 43 had been given.
you
the Hebrew, call the arts, all the land. As I say, I know, I know, I know enough Arabic
to know that that means all the land. Yes, the whole of the land. Right. That he is sworn.
Right. Mishrava. Right. There's, there's no way around this. Okay. Yeah.
Okay, first 44 and the Lord gave them red.
on every side just as he had sworn to their fathers, not one of all their enemies had
withstood them for the Lord had given all their enemies into their hands.
Not one word of all the good promises that the Lord had made to the house of Israel had
failed all came to pass.
Let's get that one one more time.
Not one word of all the good promises that the Lord had made to the house of Israel had
failed all came to pass.
I mean, that one's dirty.
in the bar and say perspicacious.
Yes.
Not one debarred.
The case.
Not one word of all the good promises.
Lord have made the house of all came to pass.
It all happened.
OK.
All the promises related to the land were fulfilled as of Joshua 21
versus 43 through 45.
It's right there.
Yeah.
It's right there in the original languages.
It's right there in English.
There is no way around it.
Yeah.
So, sorry.
dispensationalists, okay? Your whole system contradicts the Bible. The premise that there is some
land that was promised to Israel that God didn't give them contradicts the Bible. If you need to
take a moment, you can pause and come back. You can go read this for yourself, you can read it for
yourself in Hebrew, you read for yourself in Greek.
Yeah, I did again today.
just to make it. Sure. It is not ambiguous. There's no ambiguity. There is no wiggle room here. Yeah.
Right. Yeah. This is it. Okay. Now, as we mentioned before, there's another bit that's
inseparable from that, right? Taking the land is inseparable from what?
From dealing with the giant clans. That's right. Joshua 11 talks about that. Right. Okay. So we're
We're backing up now 10 chapters.
So Josh, you're left.
in starting with verse 21. And Joshua came at that time and cut off the
unacheme from the hill country, from Hebron, from Deber, from Anub, and from all
the hill country of Judah, and from all the hill country of Israel. Joshua
devoted them to destruction with their cities. There was none of the unacheme
left in the land of people of Israel, only in Gaza, in Gath, and in Ashtad
as some remain. So Joshua took the whole land according to all that the Lord had
spoken to Moses and Joshua gave it for an-
to Israel according to their tribal allotments,
and the land had rest from war.
Okay, so number one, right?
Here's that inseparable piece, the Onakim, the Giants, right?
We're all driven out.
There are a few stragglers,
we'll come back to them a little later in this episode.
Who fled to some of the Philistine cities.
The Philistines had five main cities,
Gaza, Gaut and Ashdod, were three of them.
And so some some some's where I did flee there, right? But within the land given to Israel there were no
Giants left and so once again
Joshua levers 23 Joshua took
Call the arts the whole land all the land
According to all that y'all it spoke in Damascus, okay all of it and he gave it for an inheritance to Israel
according to their tribal.
allotments. So notice remember the land is a sign of the future larger promise but the
sign of the land that inheritance is received and distributed by a guy named Joshua or Jesus
if you're being, they think about the Greek.
We can split the difference.
use the air make yesua yeah no okay but that's an important you know not to hammer on the
typology like a little bit too obviously yeah yeah so but now so we've talked about these two
things we talked about on the one hand God gave these allotments down to the clan and family
He gave them, he gave it all, he gave all that.
land, right? But the Israelites did not take possession of all that land, even their share,
right? As we talked about last time, our dispensationalist friends leave out the fact that that was
promised to Abraham's descendants, he's the father of many nations, so Moab got a piece of that,
Adam got a piece of that, etc. But even just the peace from Canaan that was supposed to be given to
the Israelites, they never took possession of the whole thing, right? But we're told God gave
of the whole thing, promise.
fulfilled. This is what our dispensationalist friends are pointing to when they try to say
that the promise hasn't been fulfilled. They say, well, Israel never took possession of that land,
therefore God didn't fulfill his promise. This is a problem. But yeah, because they that's not what
it says. Because what the text here explicitly says is, no, God fulfilled all of the promises,
but the people did not take possession of them, right? Meaning...
There's a distinction between God giving and people receiving.
This is a good sorry Calvinists moment. Yes, yes, because ultimately, as far as
dispensationalism is from Calvinism, it was invented by a Presbyterian people.
Oh no, it comes out of Calvinist coveted theology. It's a warped version of it, but that's where it
came from yeah yeah
That's the critter what spawned it, right?
And so what's happened here is that people have taken
Luther's reading of St. Paul, which is wrong,
which is the idea that there is no distinction
between God giving something in a person receiving it,
which has made even more ironclad by Calvinus
than it was by Luther, right?
that the human is inactive.
The human is passive. So if God gives you faith, you have faith. You don't have to voluntarily or otherwise receive it.
Right. And the Calvinist system, God regenerates you, meaning you are dead and could do nothing. Now,
I don't know where they're getting that definition of dead. Last I checked that meant your soul and your
body were separate, but their version of dead is that you're an inanimate object.
it God then acts upon it for a generate you
Okay, so they take that bad reading of Saint Paul, there is no distinction. And they try to read that
back here into Joshua and say, well, if God gave them the land that they would have had to receive it.
Yeah. Therefore, he can't have given it to them. And so with the text that we read repeatedly
explicitly said that God gave it to them, their whole view kind of shipwrecks.
This is what I've talked about before when we did the episodes on how to read the Bible about reading the Bible forwards, not backwards.
Yeah. Right. Don't come to some understanding you think works of something in the New Testament and then try to read it back in the Old Testament.
Understand the Old Testament and then you will understand the terms and ideas and patterns that the New Testament writers are using to talk about Christ.
Right.
So this
in Joshua of God giving and the people not receiving is crucial to understanding what St. Paul is actually saying in like Romans.
Yeah, because I mean, and I imagine some people might look at this and say, well, I'm using the New Testament to understand the Old Testament, which
Okay.
That requires you to understand the New Testament first.
Right.
It's like, well, on what basis are you understanding the New Testament?
16th century. Yeah, right. Right. Right. So you're actually using John Calvin to understand the Bible.
You're using the Calvinist tradition or the Puritan tradition or some other tradition to understand the Bible. That's what you're doing. You're not using the New Testament to understand the Old Testament.
You're using that tradition to understand the whole Bible. Right.
So St. Paul's one of his central arguments.
in the book of Romans is. Right? He has non-Christian Jewish people arguing to him,
as many Jewish people will still today, by the way, if Jesus is the Messiah, why haven't the Jews
accepted him. Right? If God sent his Messiah, if God gave...
his Messiah and giving and receiving are the same thing. Why haven't the Jews received
their Messiah? Yeah. And central to Saint Paul's argument is no, there's a distinction between
God giving and people receiving. Yeah, you can give a gift that the person does accept.
And the people in Joshua, the tribes, the clans, the families who receive the inheritance
that God allotted for them are the ones who what?
Who?
faithful who faithfully did what God commanded them to do when he commanded
them to go and take possession of that land. When they were faithful to that,
they received it. I mean, yeah, this is one of the themes in the Torah. If you do
this in obedience, then you will get this. If you do not do this, then you will not
get it and you might even have bad things happen to you. And the ones like Dan
and several of the other tribes who were not faithful did not receive it.
Yeah, did not receive the land that God had allotted to them did not only the inheritance
Not in my condensed case not only did they not take the land that they were supposed to take they were obviously idolaters
Yes
Yes, they're faithless and countless ways
Yeah, so St. Paul says now we have a new Joshua
Right
Yeah, new Yeshua a new Jesus, right?
has received the inheritance from God and distributed it.
But who receives it?
Right, the fact that he did that
doesn't just automatically mean that everyone receives it.
Those who are faithful receive it.
Those who are faithful receive their share of the inheritance.
It's one of the central arguments of Romans.
and it's drawn from this paradigm in Joshua.
Right?
But you got to set aside stuff like dispensationalism,
that's unbiblical, that contradicts
what the Bible actually says,
and go with what the Bible actually says,
which is that God can give you a gift.
God can allow you an inheritance.
And if you are unfaithful, you will not receive it.
But if you are faithful, you will receive it.
It's really simple.
And once you start thinking that way and go back and actually read the Bible, both the old and New Testaments that way,
you'll start to wonder why you had all of that silly systematic stuff in the first place because it's pretty straightforward.
Leave there in the Bible once you're just reading it.
Yeah.
And you're not tying yourself up in knots to try and make some system like that work that just doesn't fit
Or in this case, directly contradicts what the text says.
So yes, so land promises done fulfilled, right?
Was a sign of what was to come.
But not everyone received the benefits of those problems
only the faithful did.
Yeah.
And then, I mean, and then the next book,
After Joshua
Yeah. Right. It doesn't go super well. And then yeah, and then we get into the period of the judges,
part of which, so the period, the book of judges is not in chronological orders. We just saw an example
of right. Chapter 18 takes place before most of the other events in that book. Because it's giving a
finer description of an event that happened in the book of Joshua. Yeah. Right. So the book of judges
is it's kind of all over the place that way, but which is fitting because it's
describing a period of just anarchy.
Right. It says, you know, in those days, there was no king in Israel.
Everyone did what was right in his own eyes.
You know, this is not some sort of like a,
a democracy.
Yeah, or, or you know, a,
a narco capitalist paradise where everyone just gets to
govern themselves, you know,
yes, everyone is free.
Free to live a life that is
Nasty British and
short. Right. I mean, I mean, you're like, if you read through just like I you know,
people, he should just try to sit down and just read the whole book of judges in one shot.
Try that sometime rather than just few verses or read the whole thing. You can watch.
It just keeps getting worse and worse and worse.
Yes. The mayhem continues to escalate. Yeah. Right. Like we, we, we stopped in 18.
We didn't get into the concubine being chopped into pieces or the Israel civil war or yeah,
you didn't know that stuff was in there because Sunday school stopped after Samson. I know.
Right but...
And gang rape, I mean, she's
angraped first. And then they
I mean, it's yes, horror.
There's horrific stuff in the
book of judges, right? And that
showing the way everything was
this chaos at mayhem, which is
what the exact opposite of what
the Torah was aimed at, right?
Right.
Right. And there's this descending
quality of the judges, you know,
the Nadir of which is a Samson,
people love it when I talk about
Samson.
But we did a whole episode where we talked about him that enraged a lot of people.
I'll have you continue to cope and see everything we said in that episode is true.
But the thrust for our purposes tonight, the thrust of where we get in the book of judges
is that to have any kind of good order, let alone the kind of holy order that is described
by the Torah.
in a society requires a king.
Yeah, requires some kind of hierarchical leadership.
Yep.
Not just cats.
Because it turns out that everyone doing what is right in his own eyes is not great.
So on that bombshell, we will take our first break and we'll be right back with this episode of The Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung.
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation
of the epistles of St. Paul, disconnected from any historical reality. But Paul
operated.
during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish world.
In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations,
Father Stephen D. Young surveyes Paul's life and writings,
interpreting them within the holy tradition of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's epistles,
which deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in 1st century Judaism,
The young
hopes to unsettle commonly held notions and help the reader reassess St. Paul in his
historical context.
Available now at store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
A F radio.
A welcome back everybody.
Um, the call board is lighting up.
We have some excited people.
Yeah, yeah.
I wonder what I know.
No, no, it's good.
It's good.
I think we're good.
Yeah.
And actually, one of our callers is even named Dan.
That's very sorry, man.
No, no, we're not going to take you first.
Dan, sorry.
You're not first.
You're not first, but we do have someone.
the other. We do have Brennan from Jacksonville, Florida, who has a question about just
sensationalist reading Joshua. So, Brennan, welcome to Lord's Spirit's podcast.
Thanks, Father Andrew. Can you hear me? Yes, we hear you. What is on your mind?
Well, first I just want to say I met you when you came to our parish in Jacksonville
and I came up to you and I said, Father, Andrew, I love your work, but you were way too
soft on Dr. Orland.
I think you have me confused.
Yes, probably with the Mars troll that I'm working with here tonight.
Yes.
And for the record, it's because
Portland was still...
The shine was not off of his nice guy act yet.
And so part of why I think that interaction was a success is I got his veneer to crack a little.
I thought the internet just
existing in the eternal now, everything is happening right now on the internet.
But that's not why you called Brennan. Surely you wanted to talk about something other
than Dr. Gavin Orland. Van Hagar reference.
Of course, I just wanted to apologize, especially to Paul Bestie.
Yes, that is a dig to dig.
He doesn't have feelings.
He doesn't have feelings. So you don't have to apologize to him.
So my wife and I have been loving your podcast.
And we have a running joke or a catacuzon,
catacuzon class that we have to mention
your podcasts at least once.
And I just wanted to ask about the ending of Josh
because I read it, you said in your last podcast
that the ending of Josh was,
that all the land had been given to Israel
and I found it and I just thought,
what would my dispensation of friends
who even served in Israel for decades?
They've definitely read that.
How was they? How was they?
respond to that? Is there some promises, no later profits that allude to that? Like what is our hope still in it? It has already been given to them.
I mean, I.
Yeah, I mean, obviously, we think it's a profound misreading of the scripture.
But I mean, some of the way that it's interpreted a lot of it, Frank, and we don't need to go back into this deeply because we talked about in the last episode, but a lot of it is bound up in.
modern
geopolitics like the sense of, well, you know, all the promises haven't been kept. And so therefore,
you know, we need to let the modern, we need to support the idea of the modern nation-state of
Israel taking these particular pieces of land. You know, that is one of the ways that it often is.
And so, I mean, dispensationalism has had a big impact, frankly, on the foreign policy of the
United States. But I personally don't, I mean, maybe you know, but there's...
better than I do, but how they, how they, how they, how they, how
exactly they read that stuff to make it all seem like you're
here to hold to them. So when I point that out to people, I
mean, I just have to be honest, I have not gotten any kind of
real answer. I've gotten a lot of cope. Yeah. I mean, and I've
pointed this out to people who are teaching this stuff. We're
going from like church to church doing seminars. Right? With
like, you know, PowerPoint presentations about dispensationalism
in the end times and stuff. And I point this out to them in Joshua
like they've never seen it before. And I get a lot of stuff. Well, that must be referring
to a different set of promises and like what set of promises. And then I point them to
the not one word of all the promises, right? It's like, and I don't get anything. But I
think like Father Andrew said, you know, it's an obvious problem in the brush and side
and they don't read it. And they don't, you know, and I mean, hey, if you're a dispensational
out there and you can
you have a really good explanation of that verse that you think you can convince us call in.
Yes, but because I haven't heard one. I'm just being honest when I put this up to people.
But I think Father Andrew is pointing at something that's important because
there's a sort of hermeneutic circle
where they say, okay, well,
This sensationalism before 1940.
48 predicted that there would be a new nation of Israel.
And now there is, therefore, it must be true.
And the reason I say it's a hermeneutic surgical is that that validation has then led to political
support for Israel, which has led to, you know, US political and monetary support for
Israel has led to further success for the nation of Israel, which then is interpreted as further
proof that dispensational is
of his true, which leads to more support for his right, and it just forms this circle,
right, this sort of self-validating circle. And so I think the focus is on that, not on these
things that might disprove it. It's sort of the same thing I find with my Calvinist friends.
When I take them to certain passages outside of Romans 9 through 11 Ephesians 1,
You know what I mean?
it's three Romans five, right? Take them outside of some of those passages that they're used
to reading and show them something that seems to very obviously contradict Calvinism. You get
the oh, well, this is a difficult passage to interpret. Wow. And so we need to use these
other clear passages and these other places to interpret that difficult passage. And by interpret
that difficult passage they mean. Ignore that because these other ones seem really clear
me. Well, yeah, and I mean, I think there's a little bit of that going out with this
sensationalism too. They have their proof texts and they say that those are quote unquote
clear, but I don't know how you get clearer than what we just read at Joshua. Right.
And I think for most of these people, I believe that they come by these interpretations
honestly. And by that, I don't mean that they honestly sat down and studied it and, you
know, although maybe they did, but rather that this is the tradition that they received.
And so it's.
It's self-evident to that.
I mean, honestly, like, like, this goes
all the way back to the Reformation, really.
When a lot of the big debates were happening
between Martin Luther, like in these first few years, right,
after, you know, 15, 17, these big debates were happening
between Martin Luther and these Catholic apologists
that he had conversations with and debated publicly
and this kind of stuff.
They would say, look, you can't...
just say that that passage of scripture means that. That's just your opinion, buddy,
when we've got, you know, however many centuries and thousands of years and everyone in the
Catholic church saying this, and he essentially said in response, and I checked this because I was
curious about it because I couldn't believe it initially, but I checked this. And he essentially
says in response, what you hear almost every single evangelical say these days about how it is that
that they know that their interpretation of Scripture is true, which is
is essentially the Holy Spirit illumined me and I know it's true, which solves no
herminatedical problem. It doesn't because when you have people disagree and each
person says, oh, this is what the Holy Spirit is telling me. Okay, well then which one
is the Holy Spirit with or is he wants inspiring all of them to disagree with each
other? I mean, that doesn't make any sense. But I think that most people, they think
that this just simply means that that the Bible means this, the dispensation is
obviously
that Calvinism is obviously true because when they read the Bible that's what they see
because frankly that's what they've always been trained to see. And in Luther's case he wasn't
always trained to see that he came up with a lot of that stuff, right? But everybody else
from then on that's an inheritor of the Reformation has inherited that or has inherited whatever
particular interpretation their part of the Reformation Churches has adopted.
You know.
So, yeah, I mean, most people, if you say, if you were to say to them the stuff that we
just said about those passages in Joshua and elsewhere who are in the dispensationalist
world, most of them would simply say, well, you're wrong or whatever, a few might say,
huh, and then we could have a conversation potentially.
But I mean, but most people are impervious to having their their paradigms punctured completely
over the own.
Yeah.
That's a rough ride, go through.
Right. Right. Think of how many, like if you are a diet hard dispensationalist, think
of how much you would have to change about your opinions, especially right this moment,
you know, to give that up. It's a lot. That's a lot. So I hope that helps Brennan.
Definitely. Thank you for all this. All right. Thanks for calling. Okay. Next we're going
to take John and it says from LA, but I don't know is that lost in.
Los Angeles or is it Louisiana?
Where are you, John?
Hey, hey, father's Los Angeles.
Los Angeles, the other LA.
Are you literally in Los Angeles?
Yeah, literally a big city.
Oh, wow, okay.
Yeah.
Is this the first person from Los Angeles?
I don't know.
I grew up in Southern California,
so I just know that most of Los Angeles
is not actually Los Angeles.
Yeah.
But you are actually in Los Angeles.
Right in the smack middle, yeah.
My folded it to the back.
My first thought when you said that was like, well, I hope he's okay.
I hope he's not ducking, you know, in some alley somewhere calling us, you know, anyway.
No, I'm on a sidewalk.
No, actual Los Angeles is not that bad compared to some other.
Oh, okay.
Yeah, area.
I'm stereotyping, I know.
But I recently went to Northern California and I, anyway, we won't go into that.
That's a different state.
Northern California is a different state.
It kind of is.
And they will find that several times actually.
So John, it's my understanding
that you have a question about the amalcites.
Is that right?
Yeah, yeah.
So this was back to an earlier part in the conversation
where father Steven, you mentioned that it was never
commanded for the Israelites to go in
and just mass water everyone.
but rather it was more about the...
ending the ritual practices of these giant clams. And so my question is there's a verse
and Samuel that mentioned Malachi and is often used today in some unsavery context to justify
genocide and other things. And it mentions Saul speaking to or no Samuel I believe is speaking
to King Saul and his commanding them to not spare women and children in the form of the
Amalify clan for what they did to the Israelites and Egypt.
And so my question is how does the Amalify differ from their other giant plans or do
they?
And how should we confront the people who use this verse to justify some despicable things
today?
Yeah.
Well, I'll answer the second bit and then I'll let Father Stephen take off from there.
I mean, God commands certain people that are not me to go and do something with other people
that are not in front of me and have been dead for many, many, many millennia.
And I'm supposed to look at that and say, oh, God is clearly letting me do this other thing
to these other people, and in fact I'm supposed to do that.
Like...
No, not every commandment that God gives applies to every single person in every single situation.
It just does it.
God sometimes says, go do this for these people and not for everybody.
So there is no general commandment in the Bible to take vengeance upon your enemies.
Right.
In fact, it literally says the opposite.
Quite the opposite.
Yes.
It is the Old Testament.
Right.
is hardly anything.
new in the new testament in that sense.
Right.
So, yeah.
Okay. Yeah. Father. I mean, so with the amylicites and the other giant.
The amylicites are a giant clan.
There are a couple things that are interesting about them.
One of them is that technically they're an Abrahamite giant clan.
They're actually come out of the edomites.
Okay.
And their forebearer amylac was born through relations between his father
other and someone who
is called the daughter of Lothan, the daughter of Leviathan. That gives birth to Amalek,
right, the original. And so the main thing that separates them from the other giant clans
is that they were uniquely belligerent toward Israel. It wasn't that they were somewhere
sinning and God brought some Abrahamites to judge them. It's that
They tried to exterminate Israel when Israel was at Mount Sinai.
They attacked Israel too.
It's like an at Mount Sinai while God was present on Mount Sinai.
And the text actually says when God is commanding that the Amulakites be destroyed, that they
dared to lay a hand upon the throne of God.
And so they were sort of uniquely belligerent toward Israel among the giant tribes.
and made it their goal to exterminate Israel.
Yeah, and in a lot of the,
I was saying a lot of the hymns
related to the feasts of the cross.
Amalek shows up over and over again,
you know, the Israelites defeating Amalek
is connected with the cross
defeating all of the demonic power.
Because that's that's the episode where Joshua,
so they had to hold that and had to hold his arms up.
Yeah, when they fought Amalek, I'm out signing.
So what's going on then with Saul,
And we're going to touch on this briefly in a little bit, but only very briefly.
So it's fine to talk about it here.
What's happening with Saul is that Saul has...
There aren't many amulakites left at that point.
And Saul has captured the king of the amulakites, basically their head, their leader, their chief
ton, right?
This guy named Ag Ag.
It's a great name.
Yes.
And this little scene by the way in House of David is one of the few things I did that
actually made it onto the screen as far as I.
know in terms of consulting. But the actor might be doing an actual
ugrinic death curse of that scene that I consulted with him on how to pronounce. But anyway,
so Saul had captured sort of their chief in Ag Ag and the commandment from God had been that
Saul was acting as God's
against the Amulakites. Right? And so this was not like about taking prisoners, taking slaves,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah. This was about you are executing justice. Right? But what Saul had done,
right? What Saul had done was he had taken the king, their chief didn't as a captive and was
is parading him around to show...
how great Saul was in having won this military victory.
He had taken the women in children as slaves,
the women probably sexual slaves,
probably concubines for himself.
And he had taken all their livestock and stuff
and sort of booty, right?
None of which he was supposed to do.
And so it's actually kind of a funny scene
in for Samuel because Samuel shows up
and says to Saul sort of like,
Hey, uh, I-
And here's some animals nearby.
Those wouldn't happen to be the Amulacite livestock would they?
And Saul's like, oh, you know, I kept a few of those alive
so I could offer a sacrifice to God.
Yeah, that's the ticket, right?
I hear those bleeding in Amalekite.
Yes, and it's sort of doing this whole song and dance.
And that's why there's this judgment
against Saul from that episode.
Because
rather than serving as the minister of God's justice,
which is what the Israel-like King was supposed to do,
he was in it to enrich himself to display his own power
and wealth for his own sexual gratification, et cetera.
So he was behaving in this kind of obscene way in general,
but especially when he had been given this other command.
this other command, that there should be no more amulacates.
And the language there about not sparing the women and children
is the same language you see in Joshua.
And yet we see Caleb.
Yeah, he converted, right?
So conversion would still be possible there.
Yeah.
Well, John, I hope that helps.
out there in Los Angeles proper.
It does. Yeah, no, that really clarifies it.
Yeah, well, thank you, Father, so much that really put some
some questions to these and difficult questions.
So thank you. Great. Great. All right. Thank you for calling. Okay.
We're going to take one more call and then we're going to move on.
So we have Cole calling from great state of Texas.
It's cold.
Oh, Lord of Spirits.
Oh, no.
Wow.
Yes, Cole, yeah, he's all that.
Cole, welcome to the To a Closed Spirits podcast.
He evening for good evening.
My question.
I have evangelical friends that have told me about the potential
the third temple in Israel and how there
Obviously for eschatological reasons, they're pretty excited about it.
And they're being sacrifices in the temple and all of the things that would entail a third
temple.
How should we respond to that?
And would there be, is there not an issue with there being sacrifices potentially?
This is probably a fairy tale.
thing, but are there, are there, would there potentially be issues with there being sacrifices
in a physical temple like that? And I know that in North Doxie, we obviously have
sacrifices of incense and, you know, the Eucharist is a sacrifice with that,
BA problem for us. Or what would, what would be the answer to that?
Yeah, dispensationalists in Texas, huh? Who, who, who to thought?
Right, so I mean a bunch of things one could say number one Christ is that temple. You know he says that the temple of Ezekiel is Christ.
But also it's been traditionally held by Christians that the animal sacrifices of the temples of Solomon and the second temple.
that those were essentially a temporary thing.
to stand in until these sacrifice himself,
that is the Lord Jesus Christ,
our Messiah, until he came.
It would be attempting to turn back the clock as it were.
But it would also, I mean,
it just doesn't make sense on multiple levels from
a Christian point of view.
Yeah. I mean, there have not been
animal sacrifice.
in Jerusalem since the year 70 roughly.
Although as Father Stephen has pointed out before,
there continued to be some animal sacrifices
at a temple near, was it Alexandria Father?
Is that right?
Yeah, and we in Topolis.
Yeah, a Jewish temple near Alexandria in Egypt.
That was not the temple in Jerusalem.
But yeah, I mean, this is kind of a big piece
of the standard dispossessionals of you.
the end times. You know, yeah, the
Mitchell's Gofield reference Bible in
the notes says that they're when
when Jesus returns to the millennium,
they're going to sacrifice animals
to him there. That's so weird.
Yeah. Yeah. He is the sacrifice.
Notice I said the first edition.
Oh, does he get edited out into
later versions? Yeah, because they
couldn't justify. Yeah.
Yeah.
also should add for the record most religious Jews don't think animal sacrifice should be reinstated.
So once again, this sensationalist don't even understand Judaism. Yes, right. There's this kind of
there's this there's a similar crumb of Judaism that a lot of these people have that has nothing to
do with actual Judaism's. Yeah. So we do have to talk about though in this context, the fact that we're
You do fight the church father's talking about a third temple. It's always in the context.
of it being built by the Antichrist.
Oh man.
I'm sorry, it's true, say John of Damascus, right?
Yeah.
Besides the ex-Position of the Orthodox Way,
several other church fathers, right?
This is a thing, right?
When they talk about there being a third temple,
it's built by the Antichrist.
Now, personally, this is personal opinion.
This is personal opinion.
Uh, and I unlike some folks do not ascribe.
my personal opinions to the Holy Spirit in any way, shape or form. This is purely by opinion.
I think that is colored by the historical experience of Julie and the apostate.
Because Julie and the apostate was the last one to try to rebuild the Jewish temple.
Yeah, not because he was some kind of pious.
No, to discredit Christianity.
Yeah, right exactly.
And so, Julian the Apostate for several generations after his life.
became sort of the paradigm for what the Antichrist was going to be in the same way
that like earlier generations of Christians thought of Nero. Yeah, yeah. Some of
those later generations which in which a lot of the church fathers wrote, he was
kind of the paradigm. So having that be one of the things the Antichrist was
going to do to me, I think, is probably based on that historical experience. I
I could be wrong about that the antichrist
I rebuild the temple in Jerusalem, right?
But if that turns out to be true,
that's also kind of bad news for dispensationalists.
Like, they're literally setting people up
to worship the Antichrist in that case,
which by their own reckoning would be bad.
Yeah.
Now, Cole, we leave it to you
as to exactly how to communicate this to your friends.
But we're giving it to you out.
We're giving it to you straight.
Be personally, why are you invoking
the worship of the Antichrist?
That would be what I would.
But other people have other approaches.
That's right.
Is that is that is that helpful call?
Yes, that's very helpful. Thank you very much.
All right. Thank you for the lines of the evil one or spreading.
Anyway, go ahead.
Thank you. Thank you, Father.
All right, thanks.
Okay.
So, um, all right, we just finished up with the energy of the book of judges.
and that there is need for a king.
Not the
cool kind. Yeah, not certain. Gator die, dude, like the uncool kind of anarchy, where you know,
where you can buy an inner named and murdered and mayhem has happened. You can buy energy stickers
down at the mall. Remember malls? I remember malls. That's right. You don't know how much I've lost
by losing malls because I grew up in Southern California. And so I could go anywhere in the US
with Nay the World and go to a mall and be in a little
of Southern California. That's true. Like to wherever that was and feel at home. I'm reminded though.
There was a hot dog on a stick. Yeah. George Julius. Man. Yeah. I remember, I mean, I'm sure you
remember in the 80s, remember how there was a whole genre of pop singers that their whole thing was
that they performed at malls. Oh, yeah. Tiffany. Right. Tiffany was the big one. And you know, like
one of the things that brought that home for me, I don't know why, you know, maybe Tiffany came
on the radio and I decided
to look her up, whatever. And I found out her last name. Do you know this father?
I'm not aware. Her surname is Darwish. She's Lebanese. Yes, yes. I think she's from a
Mariner family or something like that. So next time you hear, I think we're alone now in the
radio, you know, you should think of Lebanese Americans. So there you go, everybody.
I prefer weirdels. I think I'm a clone now
There's always too much time. Let's just take that
as it were. Yes, yes. I think he's a Bosnian background actually.
Yankovic. Weird Al. We're now yet. Bosnian or Croatian maybe. I think maybe Croatian.
Maybe that's it. Yankovic could go a couple of ways. Yeah. Yeah.
All in that region of the world. Right. And they'll all be very angry if you get it wrong.
Okay. So we're following the arc of the history of Israel. Things they're not looking good
there at the end of judges so so
They, they, they, they, they at worst before they get better spoilers.
So what's next?
Right.
But so a big theme with the book of judges and the whole structure of it is we need a
king.
Right.
Yeah.
And when you get toward the end, it even makes pretty clear.
We need a Judah king, not a Benjamin king.
Oh, yeah, yeah.
But that ain't the one they get first.
That's right.
And so we talked about this in a very early episode.
Cause I remember I pointed out that if there's,
if there's one thing Puritans don't like,
it's formalism and worship.
But if there's two things Puritans don't like,
it's formalism and worship and kings.
Yeah, yeah.
So we did a whole episode on the crowning of,
crowning of, you know, the...
crowning in the 19th century. Yeah, yeah, we did a couple Messiah episodes and so we we've talked about this a little bit.
Um, but all that is to say a lot of us got this Sunday school reading of first Samuel that is essentially King's bad.
Israel was rebelling by wanting a king at all of any kind. Right. Uh, problem with that.
Deuteronomy 17 in the Torah said they were going to have a king.
Yes. So, do you want to ask me about what the king should do? It'd be like. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. So do you want to me 17? Starting with the verse 14. When you come to the land that the
Lord your God is giving you and you possess it and dwell in it and then say, I will set a king
over me like all the nations that are around me. You may indeed set a king over you whom the
Lord your God will choose. One from among your brothers. You shall set his king over you. You may not
put a foreigner over you who is not your brother.
us not acquire many horses for himself or cause the people to return to Egypt in order to acquire
many horses since the Lord has said to you, you shall never return that way again. And he shall not
acquire many wives for himself. Just have to point out, right? This is the commandment against
polygamy. What could go wrong? Yes, he's still not acquire many wives for himself. Less
his heart turn away. Nor shall he acquire for himself excessive silver and gold. And when he sits on
on the throne of his kingdom he shall write for himself in a book a copy of this law.
approved by the Levitical Priests.
Obviously, he's supposed to be a biblical scholar, right?
And it shall be with a copy of the Torah.
Wow.
And have the priests approve the copy,
so he can't do little edits to get away with.
That's a pretty serious amount of script of scribal work.
Yeah.
And it shall be with them.
And he shall read in it all the days of his life
that he may learn to fear the Lord is God by keeping all the words
of the law and these statutes and doing them.
That his heart may not be lifted up above his brothers.
and the
he may not turn aside from the commandment, either to the right hand or to the left so that
he may continue long in his kingdom, he and his children in Israel. I noticed that it was
just so that he may continue. Yes. Conditionality. There it is again.
Right. And so obviously God had given these commandments for what the king should do and
how he should operate, which meant that having that kind of king would not have been rebellion
against God. Okay? Yeah. This trope you've been presented that God was the king and didn't want them
to have a human king is nonsense. It's pure nonsense. Another thing we have to blame Old Milton for.
Right? So, you know, chuck that. The problem in 1 Samuel chapter 8 is that they wanted a king like
the other nations specifically
to lead them into battle.
Yeah, this is that language, you know, to go in and come in and go out, to come in and
go out.
Like it's not talking about him, you know, going on for a stroll or, you know, going down
to the...
Yes, yes.
When I leave my house and when I go home, I want the king.
No, no, this is...
Yeah, this is about military.
Sorties.
Yes.
And the reason they want that, right, the reason they want that is, again, you have to read
the texting context, go figure.
You
tried to go to war against God's command and they said, well, we'll take the
Ark of the Covenant with us. We'll carry that out there into battle and then
we'll win, right? Like use it as a totem, right? To make God fight for them, right?
Even though God had not commanded them to go to war, right? And so God had said,
Nope, and they lost, and they lost the Ark of the Covenant.
Remember it went to the Philistines,
the Philistines had to return it and all that stuff happened.
Right.
Oh yes.
And so the people are dissatisfied.
The people rather than learning what God was trying
to teach them, right?
About going into battle.
We're just like, meh, we can't count on God
to lead us into battle.
We need a king.
Right.
That's the problem.
Be practical, you know.
Right. That's the problem.
That's why God says to Samuel,
not rejecting you because saying.
Samuel was the last judge. He's called that in the text. But God says to Samuel,
they're not rejecting you as the judge. They're rejecting me or rejecting God, right,
as the one who leads them into battle. And so they pick Saul. And that's why Saul talks about how
he's a head taller than everybody else and so good looking and blah blah blah blah, right?
Yes, but now we also have to explode
Sorry, just thinking a little queen.
Oh, anyway, so we're, I don't know what what fat bottom girls has to do with this.
But you need to lock in.
Okay, stay on top.
So it was a forever.
So we have to explain.
I know I'm ruining Sunday school left and right this evening.
but we have to explode another
kind of Sunday school myth here, and that people tend to think of quote unquote,
king Saul, like he's like a medieval king, like he had a throne,
yeah, a throne room and a castle and stuff and a government,
a government and advisors and museums.
Okay, Saul was like literally a war chief.
Yeah.
Okay, that's what he was picked to do.
And that's what he did.
Yeah, this is more like the, what is the term in Latin?
the comment.
taught us, you know, him and his bros, you know, his band.
Yes.
Yeah.
His whitey men.
He had an army, right?
And you have to remember, this is early Iron Age.
This is after the Bronze Age collapse.
Okay.
So our picture of the ancient Near East and the time of David
is way less medieval Europe and way more post-apocalyptic wasteland.
Right.
like they're literally living in the ruins of...
of these previous cities and empires that had collapsed, repurposing stones from monuments
and cities and stuff.
Later on in the text, Saul has to finally fix a big gap in the wall of Jerusalem where
the wall was broken down.
That's Solomon, okay?
David's son.
So things are kind of in rubble and ruined.
Okay, and Saul is now propped up as sort of this war chief to he didn't have an infrastructure
He didn't really have an effective way to say tax Dan
Hmm, yeah, right he could ask Dan for troops
So Saul saw as we're like megan and walking dead, right?
He is like like you know Richard the third, okay
So especially physically but anyway
So we have to readjust our paradigm of what's going on with Saul.
Okay. Later on when David becomes king, David is going to begin to build that kind of infrastructure stuff.
Yeah. Right. Saul does even really have a capital city.
Right. David's going to take Jerusalem and make it his capital. Right.
David's the one who really starts to put this stuff into play.
then Solomon is the one who does the huge building projects,
like fixing the walls of Jerusalem,
but also in other parts of Israel, right?
But then that isn't last, but we'll get there.
So Saul is briefly this kind of orchi figure, right?
And when you recast him as that,
the story with him and David makes a lot more sense.
Right, where God chooses this other person, right, who's going to take his position.
Saul never gets to establish any kind of dynasty.
Yeah, it's not like Saul lives in this big palace.
And, you know, yeah.
Yeah.
So, but the transition, as we mentioned with the caller,
has to do with Saul's failure to deal with the emulokites with the giant clan,
So if you're going to be the war chief, right, this is this is the one thing you should be good for, right?
Like yeah, this got a stuff and he doesn't do it whereas David
Right from the get go and David is introduced in the text sort of his his bonafide's right his
Claim to be oh, this is the king that God is calling is made up of what?
He kills the remaining giants
Yeah, starting with go
lie. Yeah, he does. The thing that Saul fails to do. That's why that story is so important.
That's just wow, that kid's cool. He took down a much bigger dude, right? Yeah. No, this is
the completion of the mission in Takeda. Right. So there's those last few stragglers that snuck
off into Felistia. It started with Goliath. David is going to take them out. And we read about
that later on.
David and his mighty man.
Remember, David lived most of his life as a mercenary.
The leader of a band of mercenaries,
working for the Philistines,
and occasionally for the Israelites
before he was actually king king,
and started to build the infrastructure.
That's why God identifies as a man with a lot of blood
and to say he's a man of war, a lot of men of peace, right?
But so, yeah.
So we read about him taking out the last stragglers,
the last of the Ennekeem who had escaped.
Yeah, so okay, this is a second Samuel starting with chapter 21, starting with verse 18.
After this, there was again war with the Philistines at, I don't know how to pronounce it,
gob, gob, GOB, or Job, you know, if it's a rest of the development. Then Sybachai, the Husha
Thite struck down Saff, who was one of the descendants of the giants. And there was again war with
with the Philistines at Gob.
and El Hanan the son of Jare Auregim, the Bethlehemite, struck down Goliath the Githite,
the shaft of whose spear was like a weaver's beam, and there was again war at Gath,
and there was a man of great stature who had six fingers on each hand and six toes on each foot,
twenty-four in number, and he was also descended from the Giants,
and when he taunted his rodonath and the son of Shime, David's brother struck him down.
These forward descendants from the giants and gaff and they fell by the hand of David
and by the hand of his servants.
So okay, so wait, so who is this El Hannon?
I seem to recall that some people pointed this
and say this is a contradiction in the Bible.
Yeah, and one place that says David.
David kills a lot.
Right, he killed a lot.
David killed a lot.
He's got to kill a lot.
Yeah, a lot of fun.
Okay, here's the thing folks.
We've done archeology among the Philistines.
Naliyat is a pretty common Philistine name.
Okay, so that could be a moment.
out.
records of a bunch of them who weren't giants. Yeah, yeah, yeah. So this is probably just two dudes with the same name.
Wait, there's two dudes with the same name in the Bible. What? I know. Next year you tell me there's more than one woman named Mary.
Yes. So yes, I know there are a bunch of very excited atheists out there who pointed this verse and say,
See the whole Bible is lie.
But yeah, no, it's a, it's a pretty common Philistine name.
Okay.
We have records of it.
And it's not the biblical Goliath who we have records of.
Good.
This all yeah is a, is a pretty common Philistine name.
It turns out.
Um, now the, the, the six figure study,
Chad, it's six toes on each foot.
Uh, is that all about?
Yes.
This is actually an important detail, uh, because this is evidence of what we
would today call in breeding.
Oh, right. Notice it says they're descendants of the giants. So the idea here is that it's
not just these are the actual people who escaped Joshua, right? A couple hundred years has passed.
Yeah, yeah. Okay. At least a couple hundred years has passed. Don't want to lock in a date of
of the Exodus or anything. But at least a couple of hundred years has passed. These are descendants.
What this is showing is that,
remember, the goal was to wipe out the tribes,
to wipe out the clans and their practices.
So, it's not just that some individual humans
from those clans survived
and went and assimilated and became Philistines.
It's that within Philistine territory,
these giant clan families were having descendants
and were continuing these practices, right?
So you're saying that count
Ruegan in the Princess Bride who has very possible.
Very possible.
I'm willing to accept that.
Yeah.
And so part of the idea here of David killing these last giants is that David sort of brings the establishment of the kingdom in the land to completion.
Right.
And so another place where we're going to see that laid out is the covenant that God makes with David.
Okay. Now we have to understand something about the Old Testament Covenants here.
And this is something that St. Paul makes clear in Galatians and Ephesians and Romans.
But this is also just there.
St. Paul is pointing to things in the actual text of the Hebrew Bible.
He's not just making up to sting
right. So you have the promises to Abraham as we said, right, as we've been talking about the last couple shows.
The Torah then, the covenant that is the Torah, does not sort of abrogate or re-align or rewrite those promises, right.
The Torah is an additional overlay.
to those promises. And what the Torah is concerned with is about them living in
continuing to live in, right? Keeping the land that God had brought them into. So
that their life might be long in the land that the Lord their God had given them,
right? And that's when you look at the blessings of the curses, Leviticus 26,
Deuteronomy 28 through 30, you see all the blessings of curses, it's not about
eternal life it's not about
coming like the stars of heaven. It's not about theosis. It's about fertile land, good crops,
staying in the land. Right. Human flourishing. Yes. And the bad stuff, if you don't keep the Torah,
is you're going to end up going into, you don't keep Torah, you're going to end up going into exile or
death basically to put a finer point on it. Right. Those are the things that are going to happen.
but that's an overlay, right?
The structure of the promises to Abraham,
I'm going to give you the land and the fact that I give you a land
will serve as a sign that this other promise concerning theosis
and eternal life.
And the heavenly kingdom is true.
That's its own thing.
And then the Torah comes to deal with the life of the people of Israel
in particular in the land.
So now this covenant with David is again an overlay
Right about David and the sea.
and his dynasty as king is an overlay of this and it's an overlay that bridges
between the covenant of the Torah and the promises to Abraham in a certain way.
And I think we'll see that when we read basically that that covenant gets
made in 2nd Samuel. Okay so 2nd Samuel chapter 7 starting with verse 8. Now
Therefore, thus you shall say to
my servant David, thus says the Lord of hosts. I took you from the pasture from following
the sheep that you should be prince over my people Israel. And I have been with you wherever
you went and have cut off all your enemies from before you, and I will make for you a
great name like the name of the great ones of the earth. And I will appoint a place for
my people Israel and will plant them so that they may dwell in their own place and be
disturbed no more. And violent men shall afflict them no more as formerly, from the time
that I pointed judges over my people Israel.
And I look...
give you rest from all your enemies. Moreover, the Lord declares to you that the Lord will make
you a house. When your days are fulfilled and you lie down with your fathers, I will raise up your
offspring after you, who shall come from your body and I will establish his kingdom. He shall build
a house for my name, and I will establish the throne of his kingdom forever. I will be to him a
father and he shall be to me a son. When he commits iniquity, I will discipline him with the rod of
men, with the stripes of the sons of men. But my steadfast love will not depart from
him as I took it from Saul, whom I put away from before you, and your house and your kingdom
shall be made sure forever before me, your throne shall be established forever.
In accordance with these words and in accordance with all this vision, Nathan spoke to David.
So the wording and the first half of that probably seemed a little familiar to you from some of
the stuff we were reading in Joshua, about rest from enemies, and the land being at peace,
This is talking about how David has now sort of completed that process of establishing the
kingdom in the land.
But then it transitions to this other piece.
And as we just heard it read in Second Samuel, this son, who's going to take over for David,
is speaking pretty literally about Solomon, for a couple of reasons.
Remember Saul, as his contrasted here, didn't get to have a dynasty. None of his sons got the throne.
So he never had a dynasty, but Solomon is going to, right? But notice God says,
I'll be to him a father. He shall be to be his son when he commits aiquity. I'll discipline him with the rod of men.
Distributes the son of men by my step as level not to part from him as he took it from Saul, right?
So Solomon, David's son is going to sin.
and God is going to
I'm going to testize him for it.
As we'll see, we're going to talk about that more in a little bit, but not abandon him.
Like David's dynasty will continue.
And notice he says there, your house and your kingdom shall be made sure forever before
me and your throne shall be established forever.
But now when we read the parallel passage in 1 Chronicles 17, specifically verses 13
and 14, the wording is a little bit different.
Yes
Yes. So it says, I will be to him a father and he shall be to me a son. Okay, so far the same.
I will not take my steadfast love from him as I took it from him who was before you.
Basically the same. But now verse 14, but I will confirm him in my house and in my kingdom forever,
and his throne shall be established forever.
Yeah, so the thing about him sitting in big chastisers room
moved. Yeah. Yeah. In talking about this, this son, this descendant, this son of David,
right? And rather than saying, uh, your house and your kingdom shall be made sure forever
before me, it is, I will confirm him in my house and my kingdom, God's house and God's
kingdom forever. And his throne shall be established forever, rather than your throne shall be
established forever.
So, first Chronicles makes it clear that while David's immediate sun Solomon is in view,
like in Second Samuel, again, once again, that serves as a sign of another son of David,
who is going to come later.
who is going to have an eternal throne in God's house.
God's kingdom. And so the promises to Abraham that are still pending. So David has sort of completed
those promises to Abraham that served as a sign. But now those still pending promises are here
being attached to this son of David who's going to come in the future. So the Messiah, the anointed
when the king, right, the Messiah.
the son of David, right, is going to be the one through whom, not just Israel, but at least
the Abrahamites receive the promises to Abraham. And by the fact that this is directed not
just to Israel, but to at least the other Abrahamites means that there is a sort of extra
israelicom here. Right? That the problem...
that are going to come through the Messiah, the Israelite Messiah, the Jewish Messiah.
That's who the promises are going to come through.
But those promises in that inheritance are going to expand beyond just Israel proper,
or Judah proper, that the sons of David are going to rule over.
Now then, David dies, Solomon becomes king.
Everything goes south.
in more ways than one. Yes. And so Solomon is predicted by Nathan there, sins. Yeah, a lot, a lot. I mean, it does like like Commandment 1, do not worship idols. Yes. So he does. He does.
he does that. Yes, he takes all the, he multiplies wives to himself, which do their
on to me.
he shouldn't do. He built pagan wives. He builds temples for them. We find out later that he even
built an idol to the sun god in the temple courts in Jerusalem after he built the temple.
And he builds a shrine to Molech. Molech. The child sacrifice. So he does all of these very bad things
to say the least.
And so there are consequences. There are consequences for him for this. Now that said you will see icons of Solomon.
Solomon is listed to this as a acidic sari and is a saint. Yeah, he is a saint. The reason for this is not that, you know, oh, we need to somehow reread the Bible so he didn't commit all those sins.
No, I mean it says very explicit
in there, Solomon did what was evil in the side of the little part like we don't need to have
your own opinion. It's just there. Yes. And so, but the book of Ecclesiastes in particular is taken to
represent King Solomon's later repentance. Right. That at the end of his life, he saw that all of
those things were to quote Ecclesiastes vanity. They were all empty.
Right. All those things he had spent his life chasing after. Right. It's the wisest man in the world and he did some of the stupidest stuff. Right. Yeah.
Yeah. You can be but he realized that and and repentant. Right. That's why he's he's reckoned as a as a saint.
But so there's going to be judgment against Solomon and basically that judgment is going to be he's going to lose almost all of Israel.
Yeah, not in his, not in his
generation but in his son. In the next generation. Rehoboam his son is going to end up being the king
of not much. Yeah. And God says to Solomon, like, look, it's going to be divided, but not in your day,
basically because your dad was great. Yeah. For the sake of my servant David.
Well, this is the discipline, right, that that Nathan was talking about when he made that prophecy
to David and the trial. And so the rest of the kingdom
is going to go to a fellow named Jeroboam son of Nebat, who was a very naughty man.
That's right. I mean, this is a guy like, like, don't be someone that they name a sin after.
Yeah. For the rest of the history of Israel, all the bad kings are going to be, he continued
in the sins of Jeroboam son of Nebat. That's all they have to say and you know, you're cooked.
Yeah, yeah, so okay.
So here's what it says.
in 1 Kings chapter 11 starting with verse 31. And he said to Jeroboam, take for
yourself 10 pieces, for thus says the Lord the God of Israel. Behold, I'm about to
tear the kingdom from the hand of Solomon and will give you 10 tribes. But he
shall have one tribe for the sake of my servant David and for the sake of
Jerusalem, the city that I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel. Because
they have forsaken me and worshiped Astoreth the goddess of the Sardonean.
Chimash, the God of Moab and Milkom, the God of the Ammonites, and they have not walked
in my way as doing what is right in my sight and keeping my statutes into my rules as David
his father did.
Nevertheless, I will not take the whole kingdom out of his hand, but I will make him
ruler all the days of his life for the sake of David, my servant, whom I chose, who kept
my commandments in my statutes.
But I will take the kingdom out of his son's hand, and I will give it to you ten tribes.
to his son I will give one tribe that David my sir
may always have a lamp before me in Jerusalem, the city where I've chosen to put my name,
and I will take you and you shall reign over all that your soul desires, and you shall be king
over Israel. And if you will listen to all that I command you and will walk in my ways and do what
is right in my eyes by keeping my statutes and my commandments as David my servant did, I will be
with you and will build you a sure house as I built for David and I will give Israel to you
and I will afflict the offspring of David because of this, but not forever.
Not forever. So a couple of things to notice.
Notice that when God is talking about the sin of Solomon, right, and of Jerusalem,
he primarily compares them to other Abrahamites.
Yeah, Moab.
He boasts, there worshiping, he boasts, they got a Moab and milk him, the God of the Ammonites, right? Those are the
Abrahamites through lot.
Right, who had turned to paganism.
Right, so he's making a direct...
comparison between Israel. Unfortunately, the parallel that we saw in Deuteronomy 4,
we've got to bring in the land of driving about the giant clans, continued in that they
in a parallel way then turned to syncretism and worshipping other gods.
Yeah. And Jeroboam, son of Nibat, Nibat, he decides to repeat the whole golden calf thing.
Yeah.
As if we get there.
second, but we got to notice one other thing here. Okay. Yes. Sorry. Sorry. Sorry. Yes. Notice
if you will listen to all that I command you and will walk in my ways and do what is right in
my eyes by keeping my statutes and my commandments as David my servant did. Pause. Yeah.
Yeah. I mean, it says it twice in this passage. It says that David did it all. Yes. David kept
the Torah perfectly, guess what?
That's what God says here, right?
Right.
Yeah.
But wait, I thought he committed adultery and got a woman pregnant and then murdered
the husband to cover it up.
Yeah, he did.
And then he repented like the Torah told him to.
Right.
The Torah is not just a bunch of rules that also want to do when you sin.
So David kept the Torah perfectly.
one of the
those people because it's not too hard for you. And he kept it by repenting, right? That's
going to be the difference between David and Jerobo. Yeah. Not that David never sinned
and Jeroboam did. It's that David repented and Jeroboam didn't. Yep. And then Father
Andrew was talking about one of the main things he had to repent of. Yeah. Yeah. He said
up these golden calves, which like, hello, I mean, this happens during the exorcist
turn out well. Right, but so the issue is right. He doesn't want his people in his kingdom
going, having to go to Jerusalem in this other guy's kingdom where all their religious needs.
Yeah, I mean, look, there's tourism shackles at stake here. Yes. So,
Bethel is at the southern end of the northern kingdom of Israel. And Dan is at the very far
Northern Ant.
Yes, so you have something relatively convenient to you. So they have two campuses.
There's a multi site. It's a multi site idolatrous coal.
Right. He sets up these golden calves there. Now Dan, we already know had its own priesthood going.
Right. So that's easy enough. Right. Idolatry.
And so he sets this up at Bethel and that is the state religion. That is the official state religion
of the north
their kingdom for its entire history. Yeah. The next 180 years or so until it ceases to exist.
Now a couple dynasties later because dynasties turn over fast in the northern kingdom due to
assassination. A couple dynasties later, Omri is going to establish the Omri dynasty. He's
He's going to be the most famous Israelite king in terms of what we found in archaeology.
other nations refer to Israel during the rest of its brief existence as the House of Omri
primarily
More Fem- Omri is the one who buys the hill where Samaria is built which becomes the capital of the Northern Kingdom
in Ephraim, Mike, territory
and but his son Ahab is probably more famous biblically
Yes, right and Ahab's wife Jezebel to whom Omri married him to make an alliance with the King of Sidon
And in...
And so Jezebel then brings bill worship in to overlay with the official state religion
of the golden calves.
So things just kind of get better and better.
And in case you're a little new to that, this whole story, you should know we mentioned
the divided kingdom.
The northern part is simply called Israel at this point for the 10 tribes.
And then the southern part, which is Judah and then Benjamin, right?
Yeah.
Is called Judah.
That's the kingdom of Judah.
And that's the one that's being ruled over.
by the Davidic dynasty.
Right.
And so that's what's going on
religiously in the Northern Kingdom
bearing zero resemblance to the Torah, right?
Yeah.
And in Judah, things are a little better, maybe,
in that there it's mostly syncretism.
Yeah, so they're still worshiping Yahweh
but then also some other stuff.
Also some others.
But what is going on in the temple
is primarily roughly conforming
to what they were supposed to...
to do with the Torah. It's just there's all this other stuff. Yeah. I mean by the time you get
to see it. Justiah, justiah, justiah smashes a bunch of idolatrous altars and shrines and stuff.
But then and then also like one of the details as I says that there are all these vessels that
are that are inside the temple that are dedicated to bail. Yeah. And he has to bring him all out,
burn it all outside the city. And and it's all over forever. No, after just I had dies. The
Very very brief.
All that but this is why when you see righteous the righteous kings of Israel like in a lot of harrowing of Hades icons and stuff
It's usually kings David and jessiah
Yeah
For that reason
Because jessiah kind of tries to fix the syncretism, but
It's kind of too little too late at that point. Yeah, you know by the side by the time jessiah
reigns. So yes, we leave off our second half.
ending all of these on bummer notes. It's not going to get better tonight guys. I know.
It's just how the story goes. All right. Well, you've, you've, you've wasted another
perfectly good hour of your life listing, Lord of Scrooge podcast. But nonetheless,
we're going to take another break and we'll be right back. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak
and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AS radio.
Perhaps you are a seeker exploring the abundance of the Orthodox faith, or maybe you're a young
mother wanting to share the fullness of Orthodoxy with your children and family, or perhaps
you are single trying to find shelter from unclean images or words, or an empty nester, wanting
your time with edifying thoughts, prayers, discussions, and content. Or maybe you feel alone,
and just want to find solace and comfort. Regardless of your own unique circumstances,
ancient faith radio is here to help with your Orthodox journey. Please consider partnering with
us by becoming a monthly recurring donor so that we can continue our mission to spread the Orthodox
faith and help support the spiritual lives of the already faithful. Any consistent donation,
larger small will enable us to focus on our mission unavailable.
Simply visit www.
www.AncientFate.com slash support and start your monthly donations today. All gifts are
tax deductible and greatly appreciated. Thank you.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Perhaps you are a Haberdasser in the run out of.
Phil, perhaps you have a club foot in bad breath. Oh wait, sorry. Wow.
Haberdash or that's not a word you get to use every day.
You got to take your shots when you when you get them.
I know. I know.
Yeah, it looked like we were getting a call in there for just a second, but then I guess the person hung up.
Wow, they're like, we don't want to talk to those.
That's true.
So, really, we don't have any more calls.
Because we've offended everyone.
I know. They're like, well, I'm done.
There was actually, I have to say this because I think he's gone.
There was a guy in the chat on YouTube who literally, he said,
he threw a bunch of stuff into the chat and then eventually he said,
I can't just sit here and listen to people reading the Torah in English.
I threw out some Hebrew earlier.
Earlier, I know, I know.
And then the chat very, very politely kind of gave him the bifalisha.
They didn't say that, but pretty close.
So thanks, chat.
Yeah, I mean, I could do I could do chunks of this in Hebrew.
I don't know.
That'll be value added for most listeners, but I know.
Yeah.
But anyway, so actually it looks like we're getting somebody else in.
I don't know who they are.
We're actually the couple of calls a couple. Oh
It is exciting.
It's happy.
I know.
So what I'm going to say is Mike, you know, we're going to just let you just, the first person
that connects, just drop them right in.
So, welcome to our Spirits podcast.
We have no idea who you are or what your deal is, but we're just letting, we're just opening
the door right in.
So welcome.
We're just, we're just opening the door right in.
Dave, your territory people here.
Yeah.
Guardrails are off.
Is it me?
It's you.
You, a winner is you.
All right.
Alright.
I'm Tyler Minnicks from Atlanta, Georgia.
All right.
Tyler from Atlanta.
I'm the grandson of a very heavily dispensationalist pastor,
and my parents are still heavily involved.
In Georgia, how about that?
In the eye of each church, of course, right.
I don't really know how to approach a conversation with them
on these topics without
immediately devolving into, well, I won't go there.
But is there recommendations or tips or a way that I can approach the subject with them
that would maybe result in them being a bit more open instead of immediately shutting
that down?
I mean, you know, I don't know, I don't know your, your kinfolk.
But I mean, my first thought is to say, well, maybe it's just
not a good idea to have that conversation with them, you know, talk about other stuff.
But I mean so much depends of course on the relationship that you actually have, right?
So is it in a place where I could have this?
But the thought that comes to my mind is that a lot of people who are formed by dispensationalism
often have a very strong curiosity about interest in things related to Judaism.
And I think that one of the things
I remember, for instance, the late Father James Bernstein,
who, I mean, you can tell from his name,
he is of Jewish background,
and the son of a rabbi, actually, as I recall.
He looked at Orthodox Christianity,
because he first became an evangelical Christian
and then he became an Orthodox Christian
and then eventually an Orthodox priest.
He saw Orthodox Christianity as the fulfillment
of the Judaism of his fathers, you know?
And I think that...
One potential place that might be fruitful is to show, for instance, how a lot of what's
going on in the synagogue and temple find their Christian fulfillment in Orthodox Christianity.
I mean, to me, like some of the dispensationalist people when they start to become interested
in tradition and history and so forth, they join these Hebrew roots movements that I'm sure you've
you probably heard of, which are...
basically evangelicals imagining things about Judaism and trying to kind of add it into their practice.
I mean, that's really what it comes down to on honestly, because it doesn't come from any living tradition.
It's this reconstruction sort of thing.
And I sometimes I look at those people and I'm like, you know, you guys, we're right here.
You don't have to come up with something.
We got it. It's here. It's right here.
You know, so, but, but I mean, this is your family. So you know,
them, you know them best. And openness to difficult conversations really depends so much on, you
know, the relationship itself, like what does the relationship really look like? I don't know,
Father, do you have any suggestions for conversations with dispensations?
I mean, I'm not the guy to go to for tact. But you want to tact, hire a tactician. Yeah, maybe
come back tactics but no I mean the only thing I
would say is that rather than trying to broach it directly, you can ask honest questions,
like point out those verses in Joshua and just say, that sounds to me like it's saying
that, how would you understand that? How does that fit with? And then just leave it there.
Just let them think about it and answer however they answer. You know what I mean? And
just sort of seed some of those things.
You know what I mean?
sense of like asking them honest questions, listening to their answer, right?
Not pressing it and being like, well, that is a big set, you know, trying to win, right?
Or or convince them of something.
But just throw out some of these things from another point of view, you know, that might
sort of unsettle some of the things first, right?
Because if you try to overturn the whole thing, anybody who you try to overturn their whole
world view is going to react violently.
I mean, not literally, hopefully.
But I
mean, like they're going to have a strong counter reaction. Right. Um,
whereas if you just sort of, you know, pull out a couple of Django blocks, right,
but the thing's still standing. Um, that over time can end up helping
persuade people or get people to see things a lot better than just
running and yelling. Everything you've ever thought is a lie. You know, um,
the
matters by usual approach.
I say that usually works for me, but no.
Yeah.
No.
Yes, I do get a bit overzealous in my, uh, I just want them
to experience the same thing I've experienced.
But yeah, I'll try that method.
Yeah.
And always, always pray before and after.
Yes.
Conversations like this.
Yeah.
Always, always.
Alright, well thanks for calling Tyler.
So, thank you.
All right.
Well, that's it for the call board.
So let's move on into the third half.
So we just, we left it with the temporary,
just SIAP program.
So how's it going?
The unfortunately too little too late.
Yeah.
Yes.
I mean, he did write, he did write, he did what was right in the side of the Lord.
But yes.
They weren't, they weren't ready for it.
for it. Everybody didn't have a bunch of followers who
also did that unfortunately. Right. People were not as faithful as he. So, um, yeah. So now,
as we get ready to talk about the end of the kingdoms of Israel and Judah, we need to,
and I've done this on the show before, but this bears doing because, again, we got to blow up some
Sunday school. We need to talk about what kind of time frames we're actually talking about here.
Okay.
So pre-1948, there was a nation or kingdom or political entity in the world, named Israel,
named Yitzrael for our friend who left the chat.
What do you say pre-1948?
You don't mean 1947.
Whatever.
We
BC it's BC. Yes. Yeah. So but I'm not including that right by point being I'm not including that
in the whole history of the earth there was a political entity called Israel for about 200 years.
Yeah. Like younger than you know less time than than America. Yes. So that's
that's Sol and David through the end of the Northern Kingdom.
So there was a political entity called Israel in the world.
for about 200 years of human history.
Tiny amount of time.
So that includes even the divided kingdom, which as we know starts really, you know, just
a couple generations in.
Right.
That's all in David through the fall of the Northern Kingdom of Israel.
So there is something called Israel, right, as a kind of single political entity.
Because during the time the judge is there isn't a political entity Israel.
There's the tribes.
Yeah.
They're all doing their own
thing. Right. There's no connecting or overarching anything. There you want to go Judah,
right? The tribe of Judah. From David to the exile of Judah is about 350 years, which is
better than 200 years, but still kind of a drop of the bucket compared to human history.
Yeah, so that's the Judah kingdom basically up until Babylon.
and drags them all off.
Well, right.
Right.
So this is not like a nation that was there
for a long period of human history.
Frankly, the Canaanites were there longer.
Yep.
Technically the Romans were there longer.
Yeah.
But, right, that's the kind of time frame we're talking about.
This isn't a huge span of swath of history.
This is a blank, right? So the Northern Kingdom of Israel, of course, gets destroyed,
circa 722 BC by the Assyrians. Oh, yes. The Assyrians. I mean, those A-Syrian, but by the Assyrians.
Assyrians, yes. Yeah. I mean, the Assyrians, people don't know. You guys don't know.
part of Ninova. Yeah, they're in that period of history. They are
worst. They are the worst. They're super nasty, horrifying, freaking nightmare people. Like if you
really want the whole story, go and listen to, so the Fall of Civilizations podcast, which is
magnificent, they did a whole episode on the Assyrians. And you think Florida spirits episodes are
law. Listen to false
civilizations. Most of us
have been like four hours
these days. Yeah. Yeah. But
yeah, you'll get
the whole nine yards. And it includes the places where Assyria interacts with Israel actually
is in that podcast. Yeah. Yeah. So, yeah, the Assyrians, for example, have these sort of
blood-curdling conquest accounts. Yeah. Right. Of their own conquests as they establish
this. Right. This is not other people talking about them. Great world empire. No, this is
them bragging. Bragging on them. They're doing things like hanging people's skins from
the walls of their sit yes yes
they liked to, this is frequent in their conquest accounts, they went after they took a city and
beheaded everyone, they would stack up the heads, all the kids heads in one place, all the women's
heads, all the men's heads in another place, and see which one was the tallest. You got to
imagine probably there was like people taking bets on that or whatever. Tallest pile, right? This
is the kind of stuff they did. So they would come to a city, they'd lace each to it, they'd say
surrender. If you didn't surrender, they'd wipe you out like that and commit atrocities on purpose.
because then when they roll
up on the next city, it says, hey, surrender, that city would surrender.
Right after hearing about what they did in the last place.
Right.
And you see this, when you see the siege of like Jerusalem, they at least each to Jerusalem
too, in scripture, you can see all the trash talk from the Assyrian general.
Right. He literally comes out and says, you know, yeah, I know you people are trusting in your
God's to save you. But all the cities I just conquered were trusting in this.
God's too. Right. What makes you different? Right. Yeah. There's like this bad smack talk going
on, right? With the Israelite they were brutal. And so if you did surrender to them, what happened to
you? So among the Israelites, there were some who surrendered and some who didn't, right? And so a lot
of the people in the northern kingdom just got exterminated by the Assyrians. But the cities and
regions of farmland and stuff that surrendered, they would, the Assyrians were smart enough to realize
is that...
Hey, if you take over a city or take over some land, the indigenous people there will be
willing to fight and die to try to get their freedom and get that control of their land back.
Right.
So they would take the people from the land they conquered and move them to somewhere
on the other end of their empire and then take people from the other end of their empire
and move them to the newly acquired territory.
so that all of the common people living
under the Assyrian Yoke, we're living on and working land that they had no real connection to,
no ancestral connection to. And that helped them prevent insurrections. So they didn't have to go
around stomping out insurrections all the time. They could just focus on expanding.
So yeah, very bad people. This is why, and their capital was the city of Nineveh,
This is why when
God tells Jonah, hey, I want you to go to Nineveh and tell them I'm going to destroy their
city.
Jonas is like, nope, and heads of the opposite direction.
Right.
He's like, no, I want you to destroy those people are the worst.
Yes.
So like picture, you know, God comes to you in 1943 and says, I want you to fly to Berlin.
And I want you to tell them that they are very bad and I'm going to destroy them, right?
It sounds like a good plan.
Right. Now Jonah should have had courage and confidence in God and everything, right?
We're not saying that, but you could understand the human response of, uh-huh.
Right. So like, this is an extraordinarily bad idea.
And you can also understand why Jonah gets kind of upset when the city isn't destroyed.
Right. Because he knows all the Assyrians have done and he kind of thinks they deserve it.
Yeah, right. Look, God, I know you're merciful, but do you really have to be merciful to
of them like these guys are you serious? Yeah. Right. They're the worst. And they're and
and I mean, I should just I think it's just worth saying. And then in the gospels, their repentance
at the preaching of Jonah is held up against the unfaithfulness of Israel. Yeah. The cities that
Christ preached and worked miracles in that did not repent. Yeah. So as of 722b
see there is no more Northern Kingdom of Israel. As I've mentioned before on the show, I think
a former professor of mine, Lawson Younger, actually found the Lawstripes of Israel in that
he spent years and years pouring over Assyrian tablets for essentially Israelite names,
like Hebrew names and located the villages in Assyria to which
The Israelites who surrendered were deported. Yeah
Meanwhile the people who they brought in
to
The area around Samaria the capital of the northern kingdom
Intermarried with the survivors right who were of Israel like descent and those people became the Samarins who we then
Which is why the New Testament. Yeah, which is why they have this
weird
in artistic religion. Yeah. Well, yeah, and we'll give you.
getting into the Samaritans a lot more in our next episode.
Indeed.
So then with them gone, all that's left is Judah, the kingdom of Judah.
We already mentioned it's small.
They're going to last until 587, 586 BC.
Right.
So a little bit longer, almost 150 years longer before they're deported, taken into exile
and Babylon.
But to give you an idea of how tiny the Kingdom of Judah was. Yeah, we looked this up. Yes
And the Kingdom of Judah was roughly 3,400 square miles
which is
Just about one Puerto Rico. Yes, that it is decided it was the size of Puerto Rico or or a slightly less than three Rhode Islands
Yes
Yeah, so not huge.
Not big.
Smaller than the
modern nation state by far. Yes, for sure. Yeah.
Smaller than most states of the US. Yeah. Oh, yeah, yeah.
About the size of Puerto Rico, which, by the way, is part of the United States?
We're educating while we enter. I've heard that. And much like
a bomb was taken in. We received it part of the Spanish-American war.
But we'll know. And as we already read, right in the last half.
It's preserved by God for the sake of David, for the sake of David and David's line and the son of David who is coming.
Yeah.
That King who is coming.
But we also have to point out a reminder.
We've talked about this before on the show, but you know, we've given this very bleak picture in terms of the disobedience of both the Northern and Southern kingdoms and all the wickedness.
But remember all through this, right, there is a faithful remnant.
There are people king
Josiah was one of them, but there's also just common people.
Elijah gets reminded about them by God in both the Northern and Southern kingdoms, common
people who are doing their best, albeit without the help of any kind of societal structures,
but who are doing their best for themselves and their families to keep Torah.
And to be faithful to God.
There's this faithful remnant all the way through.
So it's never everybody.
It's also, right, we tend to, we're modern people, right?
We think of everyone means every individual.
I'll take it together.
Right.
And that's not how people thought until very recently, right?
It was the exact opposite.
So collectively, Israel and Judah were completely disobedient.
But that doesn't mean every individual was.
Right.
Right? There were persons who were faithful within that, but the collective was not.
Okay? That's important for understanding what we're going to read next. So St. Paul is going to talk
about everyone who was under the Torah being under its curse, being under the curse of the Torah.
Right? Specifically meaning the curses in Leviticus 26, Deuteronomy 29 and 30, death exile.
Right, because the door...
the Northern Kingdom, Dad, Southern Kingdom, exile. Right? And he talks about that. And that's
important for understanding the language he uses, for example, in Galatians chapter 3 about
the curse of the law or the curse of the Torah. Yeah. Yeah. This is interesting. So Galatians
3 is starting with verse 10, for all who rely on the works of the law are under a curse.
For it is written, the curse be everyone who does not abide by all things written in the
book of the law and do them. Now it is evident that
no one has justified before God by the law
for the righteous shall live by faith.
But the law is not of faith,
rather the one who does them shall live by them.
Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law
by becoming a curse for us,
for it has written,
cursed as everyone who has hanged on a tree.
So they didn't Christ Jesus.
The blessing of Abraham might come to the Gentiles
so that we might receive the promised spirit through faith.
So again, when he started out of the curse of Ed,
again, that's a Protestant translation.
So, with that...
I'm not going to go through in parts. Yeah, yeah, yeah, listen to whole counsel of God
or look at it in my Paul book. But he means that person of the law, right? Everyone who
keeps the works of the Torah, right? Everyone Jewish, right? Everyone who was under the Torah
is under its curse. He means that very literally, right? They're either dead or in exile.
Yeah, at that point, it's bad for Israel. That's it, right? You but he's not saying
Right every single one of you has violated the Torah and therefore are a person before God again. This is collective
Right we're all under the curtain. We're all at exile
right
Okay, and so there's nobody who there's there aren't Jewish people around there at that time who you can collectively say oh no the
The Torah says there, you know, everything's good
Right, they're all under the curse right none of them are receiving the blessings
Okay, and so but Christ is the one who comes, right, and not only
redeems the people
from
those who are the people who are under the Torah for being under its curse, right?
But also is the vehicle through which in verse 14
Right, the promises to Abraham are received
not only by those
who are under the Torah, but also by the Gentiles, by the nations, through the whole world.
Christ, say Paul is saying, Jesus, the Messiah, ends the exile for those under the Torah
and delivers the promises made to Abraham, both to those who are faithful under the Torah
and to
who are faithful from among the nations. That's the point he's making.
Okay. Yep. And again, this is a key theme, especially in St. Paul's
Epistle of the Romans, is that the failure of Israel is not a failure of God's
promises. It's not a failure of the Torah. Right. Right. It's the failure of
maybe some, maybe most people. Yeah, it's, I mean, and this connects directly to
to it, St. Paul says, and you lay-
three when he says for all who rely on the works of the law are under a curse. He doesn't mean
your cursed if you do what the Torah says. He's saying those of us who are trying to keep the Torah
were under the curse. Yes. It's not like a metaphysical system. It's not a system. It's not a
metaphysical system. He's just talking about his people. Right. Yeah. So God has kept all of his
promises. Yep, God has kept all his promises.
But a lot of people who received the promises did not receive the fulfillment, did not receive the
inheritance, why? Because they were not faithful. But the promises still stand.
And God was still true to them. Now there's another important piece here.
Right, there's another important piece here. So as we're addressing,
right what we're leading up to tonight is we're sort of
And in tonight's episode, we're going to say, okay, here's where things stand in terms
of how the promises to Abraham are going to be fulfilled and things we'll be taking care
of at the very beginning of the Second Temple period.
And the next time we're going to talk about the Second Temple period and the history of
Israel going through that period, which I know a lot of folks don't know because a lot
of it's not in Protestant Bibles, and so you're probably not familiar with a lot of that
history.
I mean, I have some money in and stuff, but we could get into
that next time. But there's another big important piece here. And to get it this piece, we have
to read a couple of things from a couple of books of the Old Testament that are going to
see somewhat obscure, but we're going to explain why they're important. So this starts
with the prophecy that Jeremiah makes.
Yeah. Okay. So this is from Jeremiah chapter 25, starting with verse 8. Therefore, thus
says the Lord of hosts.
Because you have not obeyed my words, behold, I will send for all the tribes of the north
that clears the Lord, and for never could nether the king of Babylon my servant, and I
will bring them against this land and its inhabitants, and against all these surrounding
nations.
I will devote them to destruction and make them a horror, a hissing, and an everlasting
desolation.
Moreover, I will banish from them the voice of mirth and the voice of gladness, the voice
of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride, the grinding of the millstones and the light
of the lamp.
this whole land shall become a ruin and a waste, and these nations shall serve the king of Babylon,
70 years. Then after 70 years are completed, I will punish the king of Babylon and that nation,
the land of the Caldeans, for their iniquity declares the Lord, making the land an everlasting waste.
Notice something there, right? God is going to use Babylon, the neo-Babalonean empire,
in this case, to judge the people of Judah, right?
But that fact doesn't justify all the things
that Babylon is going to do.
No, Babylon's going to get it, too.
Yes, Babylon is also going to be judged
for its wickedness, right?
But God is going to use them as a tool.
But now, there's this period of 70 years, right?
Jeremiah is prophesying that exile will last for 70 years.
that will last for seven.
in the years. So in terms of why 70 years, second chronicles of all places sheds a little
light on that. Yeah. So in second chronicles 36 verse 21, dot, dot, dot, to fulfill the word
of the Lord by the mouth of Jeremiah until the land had enjoyed its Sabbaths, all the
days that it laid desolate it kept Sabbath to fulfill 70 years. So...
What's that all about? Why 70 years in particular? What does that do with the Sabbath? 70 Sabbath years. Yeah.
So from the end of the conquest to the exile, right, is being presented here as being 490 years.
Meaning, there were
70 times
That
Israel should have celebrated a Sabbath year
But as we mentioned they never did
Not once so this order that was prescribed by the Torah
Of every seventh year being a Sabbath and then every 50th year being a Jubilee they never practiced either of them
There's most every seventh year. They're supposed to let the land rest
you
Since they didn't do that, God says I'm going to take you out of the land for 70 years,
and it's going to rest for 70 years, the 70 Sabbath years that you owe me.
Right?
Yeah.
That you owe the land.
And as I recall during that Sabbath year, those who owned the land were supposed to
kind of back away from it and let poor people work it.
Yes, there's a leave it alone and poor people and strangers and beggars could come and
harvest the land.
Yeah
Exactly. So it's and then but then that would mean I mean that's a risky thing to do. That means you're relying on God.
Right. You're relying on God. If you say okay every seven years, you're going to take a year off from your job. Right. I mean, that's kind of what it would be. Yeah. You know, and you're not going to get paid during that year.
But go to take care of it. Yeah. But so why is this such a big deal?
right the Sabbath year
If you're going to make a list of the commandments that the Israelites broke, yes, Sabbath years
on the list somewhere.
But I mean, is it that big of a deal?
If it sacrifice way higher, right?
Like, right?
Idolatry, sexual and right.
Right?
Like, there's a lot of stuff over, oh yeah, you didn't practice the Sabbath year, right?
Like I said, it's on the list.
So why is this one?
being presented here, that sort of paradigmatic.
The reason this is paradigmatic is that as we've been saying for the last two episodes,
the Torah describes a social order.
Describes an ordered way of life,
an ordered collective way of life for the people of Israel.
As we've also said in both of these last two episodes repeatedly and shown as we've gone through the history,
that order
that's prescribed by the Torah was never realized
in the actual history and life of the people of Israel.
And so what this is saying to us,
Jeremiah and Second Chronicles are saying to us
is that they never kept it, they never practiced it,
they never followed it.
And so God is going to act to establish that order.
that in the exile God is beginning to act to establish that order. And once again,
remember the idea of a sign with a prophecy. God says beforehand that it's
going to last for 70 years. So then when it does last for 70 years, you can say,
ah God established his order, the order described in the Torah in this one point.
then he will certainly act in the future.
to establish the fullness of that order, the fullness of that way of life. And as we've already seen
that action, according to the same second Chronicles, is going to happen through the Messiah.
So the expectation, as we enter into the exile and beginning the return from the exile after that 70 years,
the expectation is that God
going to intervene. He's going to intervene too. And here's just something we could say more. But
number one to free them from the curse of the Torah, meaning reverse the exile.
Right? And as part of that, restore Israel. But when he's restored Israel, he's going to restore both
parts. He's not just going to bring Judah back from exile. But he's also going to somehow restore
the Northern King. He's gonna restore all 12 truffles.
in reversing the curse of the Torah. He is going to intervene, he's going to act to establish justice,
the justice, the order prescribed by the Torah, meaning he is going to justify his people. He's going
to set things right, the way they should be. Not just tell them, here's how to do it, but he is going
to do it.
A stat he's going to establish his kingdom for
forever, not just provisionally, not just a sign of his kingdom and the earthly kingdom
of David, but his actual kingdom forever.
And he is going to enthrone the Messiah as king over that kingdom.
This is the expectation.
And so what we're going to be talking about next episode is going to be how that expectation
gets shaped and even transformed over the course
of the second temple period due to political realities and other things that happen historically.
And then how this plays out into the New Testament
with the New Testament text being all of them second temple Jewish literature.
Well here we are at the end of this part two of uh is it still a three part series father?
Are we going to three part? Well I mean we're doing a third one so
Okay
So, will there be a fourth or with a fifth?
You never know.
But in an event,
so last episode and this episode
would be quite understandably have
done a lot of talk about dispensationalism.
And I think it's important not just as a kind of
theological punching bag,
but because at least for people who are listening to us
in the English language,
Because we know that most of you are Americans.
Although, you know, we had some checking in from a number of
disparate places throughout the world and we're very happy to have everybody,
that dispensationalism has affected a lot of religious thinking, Christian thinking in America,
and as we mentioned, also even our foreign policy.
And while it's interesting, of course, to talk about the political ramifications of this theology,
Thank you.
What's more important to me is the way that it shapes how we think about the Bible.
And this affects people who are not part of dispensationalist denominations or traditions.
You know, it's a kind of meme that has made its way into a lot of Christian thinking in
the West and particularly in the United States.
And besides the particulars that we've discussed,
also have
has a kind of structural problem that it imposes on how we see the scriptures, how we see
what it means to be Christian. One of the projects that has been a big, big part of this
podcast, and I know especially Father for your first book, Religion the Apostles, is to
show how the old and the new testament
are really one, that it's really one thing, right? That it's not, okay, there's this
religion of the Old Testament, and then there's this other religion of the New Testament
that are related, but not the same thing.
And what dispensationalism does because it has this idea of a covenant for Jewish people,
that if they do that, then they can be saved. And then there's a covenant for Christians,
and if they do that...
than they can be saved.
And because of this sort of dividing of the world
into eras that is connected to that as well,
dispensations,
that what happens then is there's this kind of sequestering off
of big chunks of what is Christian tradition,
namely the Old Testament especially,
such that it's all kind of relative
in a certain way. We talked about reading forwards, reading backwards, you know, earlier,
but it almost introduces a kind of crypto-marsianism. And so maybe you've not heard that word before,
martianism. Martianism is a heretic of the early church who essentially says that the God of the Old Testament
is the creator God and he's wicked, and the father of Jesus Christ in the New Testament is a different God,
And he's good and love
us and wants to save us from the god of the Old Testament. You can see how ridiculously
heretical that is. But you can also see with the implication for not just hermeneutics,
but even what constitutes the scripture. Marcy basically wants to toss out the Old Testament.
And not surprisingly, he has his own version of the New Testament that edits out kind of cuts
That's a lot of stuff that seems to validate the
Old Testament. And even for Christians who will say that they believe everything in the Old
Testament, there's often the sense of, okay, well, there's a whole bunch of stuff that's here,
and it's good and true for this period. And then it gets negated, you know, a replaced or whatever
later on for Christians. And then, and this is honestly, this is the basis of, like we had the
one caller who asked about these people who think that that there needs to be another temple in
Jerusalem where they're gonna off-prop-
animal sacrifices and it's because of this sort of sequestering off, you know, these elements. Well,
that doesn't apply to everybody, but it doesn't apply to these people, to these people, you know, and,
you know, we reacted with incredulity to that because shouldn't Jewish people, shouldn't, you know,
Israelites, however, whatever, shouldn't they have Jesus too, right?
to turn to animal sacrifice in another temple is to turn away from Christ. Shouldn't they have Jesus too? Shouldn't they be Christians too?
You know, and so it's this fragmentation that's introduced by this view of the Scripture that is the problem.
It's not the scripture is not fragmented. It's one.
Father Stephen just said that the New Testament is Second Temple Jewish literature.
You don't understand, perhaps, conceptually, maybe because for a lot of people, second-time
people, Jewish literature is a relatively newer concept that they may not be familiar with.
You understand, okay, this is Jewish as well.
Well, the New Testament is a Jewish document, set of documents, really.
It represents a particular strain of one Judaism as it were at the time.
And that doesn't relativize it.
That doesn't demote it by any means because we explicitly believe this is the one that's
true.
This is the one that gets everything right.
the one that is validated by the Messiah himself, right, that the Word of God became fleshed
and dwelt among us as St. John says. And so I think, you know, if you're a Christian and
you love the Scripture, you're putting artificial speed bumps and blocks and, you know, whatever
obstructions on your understanding of the scriptures if you accept dispensations.
thinking, whether you belong to a dispensationalist
denomination or tradition or not.
You know, if you say something like,
well, that was for the Jews and then this is for Christians,
then you're, then you have accepted on some level
dispensationalist thinking.
You know, if you look at the Bible that way,
yes, of course, and we've talked about this in great detail.
There are things from the old covenant that get transformed
in the new covenant, absolutely.
But when Jesus says that not one, you know.
you know, jot or tidal as it is in the good old King James version of the law is going
to pass away. He wasn't he wasn't joking, you know, he wasn't that he really meant that.
So that means that all of it is kept. The whole Torah is kept in Christianity. It's not
a separate covenant, right? The new covenant is the transformed old covenant. It is the
renewed covenant. And that in that
new order of things that change, for sure.
But it is one, it's all one, as you like to point out
Father Stephen, St Paul did not convert to another religion.
He's a Pharisee who remained a Pharisee
and he just needed to realize, hold on,
hold on, these events have happened
that you've always hoped for as a Pharisee.
Oh, so then that means this is happening now, right?
So understanding the scriptures,
is such an important part of what it means to be a Christian. It's so so important.
You know, it's honestly like one of the one of the things I love the most when we did our first
Laura Spears conference is there's hundreds of people that showed up to this conference and they
want to know the scriptures. They want to understand the scriptures. That's why we're there.
And if you're listening as podcasts, you probably that's that's what you want. You want to understand
the scriptures, that's what we're working on here, right? And so
So understanding the scriptures part of that means knowing what these big arcs are and
how it all connects.
And so that's part of what's going on in this series of episodes about the history of Israel
is seeing what some of the big overarching narrative arcs are, but also seeing how it's
all one.
So don't let dispensationalism cut it into pieces for you.
It's all one.
Father
So Carl Bart, German theologian, writing in the early 20th century, said the great threats
to Christianity that were coming along in order would be first, national socialism, which
she saw on the rise in his own country of Germany, followed by communism.
followed by Americanism.
Guess where we are today.
If you've listened to my whole council of God Bible study at Revelation, this won't shock you as much as it will if you haven't, but frankly,
the United States of America is our current incarnation of the horror of Babylon in the world.
the early 20th century it was Britain. But now it's the United States of America.
I say this as an American. And the reason for that is that America and Americanism
has basically colonized the world, but in a much more subtle way than the British
ever did. The British Empire was profoundly unsuddle in its colonization tactics.
Because America doesn't primarily colonize in the sense that they did, like going and taking
over countries and making them vassal states, right, and making them all speak American
English, etc.
America and Americanism tend to colonize the minds of people all over the world.
American ideas and ideals, right?
And that's shown by how we colonize, right?
We colonize by exporting movies.
and television shows and cultural artifacts and McDonald's and could all capitalism and
Coca-Cola all over the world, Mickey Mouse. And the most deeply colonized people by
Americanism of course are Americans. We're the ones on whom the job has been done most
thoroughly. And so we approach things.
as Americans, the perspective of American values. I have sat in graduate school classes
that had biblical studies, professors argue to me that Genesis describes the separation of church
and state. That when judges says, in those days there was no king and everyone did was right in his
so nice. That was a good thing.
They have argued to me because King's back. Something like anarcho-capitalism good, or at
least minarchism, minimum possible government. Everyone can do their own thing. Those are
kind of egregious examples of sort of importing this whole American worldview into the scriptures
as we read them.
But American forms of Christianity have also colonized a lot of Christianity.
And dispensationalism no less than the others, certainly in some of its views.
And so I mean, I started out this episode by calling a bunch of people blasphemers.
But you'll notice I said they weren't intending to be blasphemers.
They just believed something they were taught.
Why someone else who believed it?
Because they were taught it.
Right.
And it's just ingrained.
It's an ingrained idea.
We've criticized some other views over the course of this episode.
And there are just these ingrained ideas that are in our heads.
And so when we look at the Scriptures, we see them.
If we look at a passage, it seems to contradict them.
Ooh, that's a tough passage.
The ones that we can read in a way that are commensurate
with those ideas, we're like, oh, there's an easy passage.
Well, we'll interpret everything in light of that.
And we don't realize just how much we've been shaped.
If you want to understand the scriptures,
if you're ever reading and studying the scriptures,
and you don't feel like you're in a foreign country,
You don't feel a sense of uncannyness, a sense of strangeness.
You don't feel like you've left your comfortable day to day American or quasi-American or depending
on who's listening, right?
First world, Western, whatever we want to say, lifestyle and gone to someplace different.
Another place, another time, another culture, another way of looking at the world.
other set of values. Then you're not really...
reading the Bible. You're reading the traditions, the ways of thought, the ideas that have colonized
your own mind. And you're just sort of caught in this circle, in this cycle. It's hard to break.
But the only way to break it is to step outside of it.
One of the reasons.
Right, there's always madness to my method.
Right.
One of the reasons why sometimes put things in the most,
it may be not the most, but in more shocking ways
than are necessary on this show.
Maybe a little more jolting or emphatic than they need
to be is to try to help with this.
Right.
To try to really help somebody who wants to get out
of the vicious cycle.
of reading in, maybe jolt them out of it a little bit.
Maybe break a few things, right?
Do many things get cleaned up and reorganized?
I'm honestly trying to help.
My intentions are good.
Now comes May very.
But that's where we need to go.
We should always feel, as I said,
when we're studying the scriptures
like we're in a forum.
We're in a different place, a place where we're kind of a stranger.
And we're trying to understand and we're trying to enculture it ourselves.
And we're trying to fit into this other way of thinking,
and this other way of being, and this other way of seeing.
And the same thing is true.
The same thing is true when we go to church.
The same thing is true when we're in liturgical services.
When we're entering into the kingdom of heaven.
If that doesn't feel like a little bit of a foreign country to us, if that doesn't feel
a little strange, if it doesn't feel like we don't quite fit and we're going to need
to change and we're going to need to acculturate ourselves and we're going to need to learn new
language and new ways of talking and thinking in order to fit, then that means we haven't
left home.
that were still stuck in the place where we started.
Don't think from how I started this that I think America is exceptionally bad.
I don't think it's any worse than Britain.
Right?
Just our numbers up right now.
I don't think it's any worse than any other country.
But I do think that like every country in this world,
it is a foreign country to the kingdom of God.
I do think that it is.
not the kingdom, it is not becoming the kingdom, and it is not going to become the kingdom.
Neither is the nation state of Israel, or any other country on this earth.
So I hope that maybe one of the things we do on this show by breaking up settled notions,
so this kind of thing, like in these last couple in our next episode, by breaking up a lot
of these central notions.
Hopefully at least for
some folks who want to try to get there, it'll help restore that sense of uncanniness,
that sense of nod at homelessness, where we're coming and trying to understand and trying
to fit ourselves in with the things of God.
Because that's the only way we can grow and change and ultimately be conformed to the
likeness of Christ.
Amen.
Well, that is our show for tonight.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
listening. If you didn't happen to get through to us live, we'd like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordOfSpirisNationFate.com. You can message us at our Facebook page. You
can also leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordOfSpirits. If you have basic questions
about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish, head over to Orthodoxintro.org.
I'd like to ask you a question. I'd like to ask you a question. I'd like to ask you
a question. I'd like to ask you a question. I'd like to ask you a question. I'd like to ask you
and refine out of control.
do it all to get them off their feet.
And if you are on Facebook, you can follow our page.
You can join our very active discussion group,
leave ratings and reviews in the appropriate places.
All of just five stars obviously.
And also share this show with a friend.
And I'm told that this amused somebody last time.
I said it. Also share it with your enemies.
And finally, be sure to go to www.engsyfate.com
Stroke Support.
And don't make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters
stay on the air.
Crowd is here about to blow.
Waiting for me to start the show.
So cut the curtain lights, oh, I'm home.
Thank you, good night, God bless you, Christ is risen.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the
beasts, and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands
of thousands. Same.
with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.